<article>
  <title>Predicting high-tech equipment fabrication cost with a novel evolutionary SVM inference model</title>
  <abstract>
    <sentence>Accurately predicting fabricating cost in a timely manner can enhance corporate competitiveness.</sentence>
    <sentence>This study employs the Evolutionary Support Vector Machine Inference Model (ESIM) to predict the cost of manufacturing thin-film transistor liquid–crystal display (TFT-LCD) equipment.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ESIM is a hybrid model integrating a support vector machine (SVM) with a fast messy genetic algorithm (fmGA).</sentence>
    <sentence>The SVM concerns primarily with learning and curve fitting, while the fmGA is focuses on optimization of minimal errors.</sentence>
    <sentence>Recently completed equipment development projects are utilized to assess prediction performance.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ESIM is developed to achieve the fittest C and γ parameters with minimized prediction error when used for cost estimate during conceptual stages.</sentence>
    <sentence>This study describes an actionable knowledge-discovery process using real-world data for high-tech equipment manufacturing industries.</sentence>
    <sentence>Analytical results demonstrate that the ESIM can predict the costs of manufacturing TFT-LCD fabrication equipment with sufficient accuracy.</sentence>
  </abstract>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>High-tech equipment</keyword>
    <keyword>TFT-LCD</keyword>
    <keyword>Manufacturing</keyword>
    <keyword>Cost estimation</keyword>
    <keyword>Hybrid artificial intelligence</keyword>
    <keyword>Support vector machine</keyword>
    <keyword>Fast messy genetic algorithm</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <section name="Introduction">
    <sentence>Retail prices of thin-film transistor liquid–crystal displays (TFT-LCDs) are strongly influenced by the high degree of research and development (R&amp;D) uncertainty.</sentence>
    <sentence>In practice, the functions and specifications of a flat panel cannot be fully determined during early R&amp;D stages; thus, initial cost estimation (ICE) is largely based on the subjective judgment of experienced engineers.</sentence>
    <sentence>Such an ICE is only a price quoted for potential buyers and a comparative estimate for potential providers.</sentence>
    <sentence>Although knowledgeable sales managers or estimators may generate accurate cost assessments via teamwork, professionals are difficult to train and very mobile in small and medium-sized enterprises in Taiwan.</sentence>
    <sentence>Thus, experience and project knowledge is difficult to retain, resulting in such problems as loss of project know-how.</sentence>
    <sentence>The TFT-LCD industry in Taiwan, which is promoted by the government’s Two Trillion Twin Stars plan, has developed rapidly in recent years.</sentence>
    <sentence>The TFT-LCD industry is second only to the semiconductor industry in driving Taiwan’s economic growth.</sentence>
    <sentence>Notably, LCD production involves hundreds of complex processes.</sentence>
    <sentence>Each panel manufacturer typically has patented processes and production lines requiring highly customized manufacturing equipment.</sentence>
    <sentence>Producing various panel sizes is typical as the need for next-generation panels increases.</sentence>
    <sentence>Despite significant advances in tools and techniques assisting in project management (PMI, 2004), project managers (PMs) in the engineer-to-order manufacturing industry still encounter problems associated with guesswork and subjective judgment that result frequently in inaccurate estimates.</sentence>
    <sentence>These non-objective approaches result in several important difficulties that render them inadequate for general application.</sentence>
    <sentence>Notably, companies can lose market share and orders during the early marketing phase of attracting customers as a result of inefficient and inaccurate cost estimation.</sentence>
    <sentence>Although human experts can achieve a satisfactory outcome, shortfalls typically occur as managers fail to access relevant information efficiently.</sentence>
    <sentence>Generally, shortcomings in a currently used subjective-assessment or analogous method suggest a need and opportunity for improvement.</sentence>
    <sentence>Development of a deterministic mathematical model to solve project cost management problems is both difficult and expensive.</sentence>
    <sentence>Approximate inference, a fast and cost effective approach, is a viable alternative to a deterministic mathematical model.</sentence>
    <sentence>Inference is the process of deriving new knowledge from known information.</sentence>
    <sentence>When the known information changes, the inference process adapts accordingly.</sentence>
    <sentence>Cost prediction problems are complex and full of uncertainties, vagueness and incomplete or inexact data.</sentence>
    <sentence>Therefore, the inference process must fit environmental realities (Mareels &amp; Polderman, 1996).</sentence>
    <sentence>Humans can learn and process complex problems, even when faced with uncertainty, imprecision, and incomplete information.</sentence>
    <sentence>Imitating the human inference process is an effective approach to solving cost management problems.</sentence>
    <sentence>The technological marketplace has become increasingly competitive due to rapid globalization.</sentence>
    <sentence>Product cost estimation is thus critical for sales managers at companies developing high-tech equipment to gain competitive advantage.</sentence>
    <sentence>As the amount of time panel manufacturers allocate to investment and production is critical, fast and accurate estimations are essential to successful delivery of devices to markets in a timely manner, as is quality to customers in increasingly competitive markets.</sentence>
    <sentence>Although many studies of the TFT-LCD industry have analyzed raw materials, processes, supply chains, and marketing, cost forecasting of TFT-LCD fabrication equipment has seldom been addressed.</sentence>
    <sentence>The primary objective of this research is to accurately predict the costs of high-tech manufacturing equipment.</sentence>
    <sentence>This study reviews relevant literature and collects data and equipment specifications from past projects in the TFT-LCD manufacturing equipment (TME) industry.</sentence>
    <sentence>The TME costs are predicted using a novel Evolutionary Support Vector Machine Inference Model (ESIM).</sentence>
    <sentence>The proposed ESIM simultaneously searches for the fittest support vector machine (SVM) parameters within a globally optimized model.</sentence>
    <sentence>An early accurate estimate during the negotiation stage with potential clients can eliminate unnecessary bargaining and significant cost changes in subsequent manufacturing processes.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Literature review">
    <sentence>TFT-LCD manufacturing process A TFT-LCD device has three layers—a liquid–crystal layer encapsulated by two glass substrate layers (Fig 1), namely, the TFT and color-filter plates (Clark &amp; Robert, 2001).</sentence>
    <sentence>The color-filter plate is also utilized as a common electrode plate.</sentence>
    <sentence>The transparent common electrode on this plate is made of indium tin-oxide (ITO), a conducting glass, and is deposited on top of the color filter (CF) layer (Choe, 2006; Okuya, Ito, &amp; Shiozaki, 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>The cell gap for the liquid crystal (i.e., space between two glass substrates, the TFT and color-filter plates) must be controlled precisely to within a few micrometers to achieve excellent display quality.</sentence>
    <sentence>Furthermore, this gap must be uniform and reproducible throughout the entire display.</sentence>
    <sentence>Typically, transparent spacers, such as plastic beads, are placed on the glass substrate surface to achieve this aim.</sentence>
    <sentence>TFT-LCD device structure Fig 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>TFT-LCD device structure.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 2 shows a typical TFT-LCD fabrication process scheme.</sentence>
    <sentence>This scheme can be divided into three stages: the array process; LCD process; and, LCD module (LCM) process (Clark &amp; Robert, 2001).</sentence>
    <sentence>The array process stage has two manufacturing processes, namely, fabrication of the TFT and fabrication of the CF.</sentence>
    <sentence>To manufacture a TFT array, a glass substrate is first chemically cleaned, followed by deposition of an amorphous silicon (a-Si) layer on substrate top (Ibaraki, 1996).</sentence>
    <sentence>After defining the a-Si area via photolithography and plasma etching, an ITO layer roughly 50–80 nm is sputter-deposited on top of the a-Si layer; the ITO is then patterned to form pixel electrodes.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ohmic contact layer in each pixel region is then dry etched using source and drain electrodes as a mask.</sentence>
    <sentence>Finally, a protective 250 nm silicon nitride layer is deposited by Plasma-Enhanced Chemical Vapor Deposition (PECVD) and contact windows are opened (Sehgal, Mangla, Gupta, &amp; Gupta, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>The entire process resembles the manufacturing process for semiconductor devices, except for that of the glass substrate.</sentence>
    <sentence>Flowchart of the TFT-LCD fabrication process Fig 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Flowchart of the TFT-LCD fabrication process.</sentence>
    <sentence>The CF is constructed with dyes.</sentence>
    <sentence>Several methods can be utilized to deposit red, green, and blue (RGB) color dyes onto a glass substrate, including diffusion, electro-deposition, and printing.</sentence>
    <sentence>Moreover, several color-element configurations, including stripe, mosaic, and delta, exist.</sentence>
    <sentence>Among these many combinations of CF fabrication methods and configurations, the color-resist method with a stripe-type RGB arrangement is the most common approach (Lee et al., 2008; Sabnis, 1999).</sentence>
    <sentence>Between the blocks of color in the CF is a black matrix (BM) made of a dense metal, such as chromium, to protect a-Si TFTs from stray light, and eliminate light leakage between pixels.</sentence>
    <sentence>The final process is the application of a protective film and deposition of a 150 nm-thick ITO layer.</sentence>
    <sentence>During the LCD manufacturing process, the TFT array and CF substrates are then made into an LCD panel by joining the two substrates with a sealant; the cell gap is maintained by spacers.</sentence>
    <sentence>The two substrates are laminated together and the panel is then filled with liquid crystals.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the final manufacturing stage, driver circuits, the Back-light Unit (BLU) and other components, are integrated into the panel to complete the LCM (Smith, 2005).</sentence>
    <sentence>Current estimation practice and challenges Estimation accuracy is very dependent upon the amount and quality of information available at estimation time.</sentence>
    <sentence>Thus, achieving highly accurate preliminary cost estimates is extremely challenging (Berlin, Raz, Glezer, &amp; Zviran, 2009; Chou, 2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 3 shows the price quotation and engineer-to-order processes integrated with the proposed ESIM.</sentence>
    <sentence>The primary challenge in current practices is that when a sales manager contacts clients for make-to-order quotes, estimated costs are based solely on known product attributes, while the vast majority of product costs are implicitly determined in the early stages of product development for most manufactured goods.</sentence>
    <sentence>The make-to-order processes with the proposed ESIM prediction model Fig 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>The make-to-order processes with the proposed ESIM prediction model.</sentence>
    <sentence>The analogous technique is highly subjective and reliant on personal judgment, easily resulting in inaccurate estimates during analytical estimation processes.</sentence>
    <sentence>Likewise, activity-based costing is extremely dependent upon the availability of detailed design information, which is generally useful, but not ideally suited to early estimations in practice.</sentence>
    <sentence>The bottom-up estimation process is relatively straightforward and can generate good results when utilized appropriately.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, without detailed product design specifications, this process leads to inaccurate estimates.</sentence>
    <sentence>In such cases, manual estimates are unsatisfactory and time-consuming.</sentence>
    <sentence>Furthermore, high-tech companies typically lose sales personnel at a rapid rate and, thus, have difficulty retaining experience-based and implicit product knowledge.</sentence>
    <sentence>Conversely, only incomplete equipment design specifications are available during the early quotation and negotiation stages.</sentence>
    <sentence>Rapidly responding to customer enquiries using little available information is critical to securing orders.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fairly accurate predictive tools for determining selling prices before an actual device is manufactured are needed for engineered-to-order suppliers to retain competitive advantage in global markets.</sentence>
    <sentence>Cost estimation techniques Prevailing cost estimation methods typically include analogous cost estimation (ACE), an analytical estimation technique, and artificial intelligence (AI)-based approaches (Bode, 2000; Camargo, Rabenasolo, Jolly-Desodt, &amp; Castelain, 2003; Duverlie &amp; Castelain, 1999; Kwak &amp; Watson, 2005; Marban, Menasalvas, &amp; Fernandez-Baizan, 2008; Metaxiotis, 2004; PMI, 2004).</sentence>
    <sentence>The ACE process uses values of such parameters as project duration, size, cost, and construction complexity from a similar product to estimate the cost of a new product.</sentence>
    <sentence>This technique, which is frequently employed to estimate cost early in a product’s lifecycle when little information is available, requires both sufficient knowledge and expert judgment.</sentence>
    <sentence>AI is related to computer system designs that attempt to resolve problems intelligently by emulating human brain processes.</sentence>
    <sentence>As AI technology enhances the ability of computer programs to handle tasks (Haykin, 1999), employing AI models are suitable for solving project cost management problems.</sentence>
    <sentence>Various scientific and engineering fields have increased their attention in recent years on hybrid AI paradigms to achieve greater efficacy.</sentence>
    <sentence>A number of studies have demonstrated that cost estimation performance achieved by combining different AI techniques is better than those achieved by employing a single technique (Chen, 2007; Kim &amp; Shin, 2007; Lee, 2009; Li et al., 2005; Min, Lee, &amp; Han, 2006; Nandi et al., 2004; Wu, Tzeng, &amp; Lin, 2009; Wu, 2010).</sentence>
    <sentence>Fast messy genetic algorithms (fmGAs) and the SVM are two tools that have been applied successfully to solve various management problems.</sentence>
    <sentence>Considering the characteristics and merits of each, this study combines fmGAs and an SVM to develop a novel ESIM to estimate the cost of TFT-LCD manufacturing equipment.</sentence>
    <sentence>An early accurate estimate generated during the negotiation stage with clients can eliminate unnecessary bargaining and cost changes in subsequent manufacturing processes.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the ESIM, the SVM is employed primarily for learning and curve fitting, while the fmGA optimizes prediction error.</sentence>
    <sentence>This ESIM was developed to achieve the fittest C and γ parameters while minimizing prediction error.</sentence>
    <sentence>Implicit knowledge from historical cases can be obtained using the novel approach for sales managers or decision-makers during early quotation stages to overcome challenges in the TFT-LCD process equipment industry.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="The Evolutionary Support Vector Machine Inference Model (ESIM)">
    <sentence>Support vector machines and fmGAs represent recently developed AI paradigms.</sentence>
    <sentence>An SVM was first developed by (Vapnik, 1995); SVMs have recently been applied to a wide range of problems in various disciplines that include customer churn prediction (Coussement &amp; Van den Poel, 2008), reliability forecasting in engine systems (Chen, 2007), document categorization (Hao, Chiang, &amp; Tu, 2007), credit rating (Lee, 2007), content-based image retrieval (Seo, 2007), Fault diagnosis (Widodo &amp; Yang, 2007), feature selection and pattern recognition (AcIr, 2006; Kim &amp; Shin, 2007; Li et al., 2005), prediction of air entrainment rate and aeration efficiency of weirs (Baylar, Hanbay, &amp; Batan, 2009), and bankruptcy prediction (Shin, Lee, &amp; Kim, 2005).</sentence>
    <sentence>The SVM classifies data with different class labels by determining a set of support vectors that are members of the set of training inputs that outline a hyper plane in a feature space.</sentence>
    <sentence>It utilizes a generic mechanism that employs a kernel function to fit the hyper plane surface to training data.</sentence>
    <sentence>A user may select the SVM kernel function (e.g., linear, polynomial, or sigmoid function) during the training process to identify support vectors along the function surface.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, when using an SVM, users encounter the problem of how to set optimal kernel parameters.</sentence>
    <sentence>Therefore, SVM parameters must be obtained at the same time as achieving optimal parameter settings.</sentence>
    <sentence>Appropriate parameter settings can improve SVM prediction accuracy, with parameters to be optimized, including penalty parameter C, and kernel function parameters, the gamma of the radial basis function (RBF) kernel.</sentence>
    <sentence>In designing an SVM, one must choose a kernel function, set kernel parameters and determine a soft margin constant C (penalty parameter).</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 4 shows the SVM procedure.</sentence>
    <sentence>The SVM procedure Fig 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>The SVM procedure.</sentence>
    <sentence>The grid algorithm is an alternative to finding the best C and γ parameters when using the RBF kernel function.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, this method is time consuming and does not perform well (Huang &amp; Wang, 2006).</sentence>
    <sentence>An fmGA was first developed by Goldberg et al.</sentence>
    <sentence>Unlike the well-known simple GA (sGA), which uses fixed length strings to represent possible solutions, an fmGA applies messy chromosomes to form strings of various lengths.</sentence>
    <sentence>Its ability to identify efficiently optimal solutions for large-scale permutation problems means that the fmGA has the ability to generate SVM parameters C and γ simultaneously.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the proposed ESIM, an SVM is employed for learning and curve fitting, while the fmGA optimizes prediction error.</sentence>
    <sentence>This model was developed to obtain the fittest C and γ parameters with minimized prediction error.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ESIM adaptation process can be demonstrated with a pseudo code algorithm which is developed by the authors (Cheng &amp; Wu, 2009) and applied to project management effectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 5 shows the ESIM flowchart.</sentence>
    <sentence>A detailed explanation of this flowchart follows.</sentence>
    <sentence>(1) Training the SVM.</sentence>
    <sentence>In this step, the SVM uses default parameters and a training dataset to train a prediction model.</sentence>
    <sentence>(2) Fitness evaluation.</sentence>
    <sentence>For each chromosome representing C and γ, a training dataset is employed to train the SVM and calculate the prediction accuracy.</sentence>
    <sentence>When accuracy is sufficient, each chromosome is evaluated using a fitness function.</sentence>
    <sentence>(3) Termination criteria.</sentence>
    <sentence>The process stops once termination criteria are satisfied.</sentence>
    <sentence>When criteria are not satisfied, the model proceeds to the next generation.</sentence>
    <sentence>(4) The search for fmGA parameters.</sentence>
    <sentence>In this stage, the model searches for superior solutions via genetic operations.</sentence>
    <sentence>Detailed theoretical background and model architecture can be referred in Cheng and Wu’s research study (2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>Flowchart of ESIM Fig 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>Flowchart of ESIM.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Data description and analytical results">
    <sentence>The study company, located in Southern Taiwan Science Park, is a world-leading equipment manufacturer that caters to Taiwanese TFT-LCD panel manufacturers, including Chi Mei Optoelectronics, AU Optronics, Innolux Display Corp., Chunghwa Picture Tubes, Ltd., Allied Material Technology Corp., and TPO Displays Corp. An industry report for Taiwan’s TFT-LCD industry predicts that 1.2 billion LCD TVs will exist worldwide by 2015 (PIDA, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>The study company fabricates over 15 types of manufacturing equipment for TFT-LCD production.</sentence>
    <sentence>The laser repair (Repair), light-on-test (LOT), and macro inspection systems (Macro) account for 48% of total revenue for the company over the last 3 years.</sentence>
    <sentence>Since obtaining a complete collection of data for all previous projects is unlikely due to the lack of a centralized project management information system (PMIS), the primary goal is to generalize prediction capability of AI-based techniques using available project data.</sentence>
    <sentence>Based on the principle of priority management, Repair, LOT, and Macro systems were treated as target samples and thereafter utilized in prediction model development.</sentence>
    <sentence>TFT-LCD inspection and repairing equipment In TFT-LCD manufacturing, especially for large products such as TVs, display panels must have high resolutions and excellent picture quality, in particular, high luminance, a high contrast ratio, wide viewing angle and rapid refresh rates (Pardo, Pe´rez, &amp; Suero, 2004).</sentence>
    <sentence>Therefore, to ensure a high yield rate for products meeting these criteria and reduce costs, strict quality-assurance and quality-control measures must be applied by manufacturers, meaning careful inspection of panels plays a central role in the manufacturing process.</sentence>
    <sentence>Consequently, products with defects or imperfections can be identified and repaired or recycled.</sentence>
    <sentence>Panel inspections employ various examination methods that use, say, optical instruments, electrical instruments, and even the human eye (Gaillet, Yan, &amp; Teboul, 2007; Park &amp; Yoo, 2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>For example, during the LCM process, many spot-type defects can occur on the LCM surface.</sentence>
    <sentence>These defects are classified as macro-defects and micro-defects, which can be detected by macro- and micro-inspection systems, respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>Inspection of such defects is extremely important to determining whether an LCM is defect-free.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 6 presents a common macro-inspection system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Macro inspection system Fig 6.</sentence>
    <sentence>Macro inspection system.</sentence>
    <sentence>The LOT is also an important quality-control measure system used during the panel and module assembly processes when manufacturing TFT-LCDs.</sentence>
    <sentence>Generally, the process includes inspection of the panel surface, modules, and picture display quality.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 7 shows a common system for inspecting LOT.</sentence>
    <sentence>Light-on-test (LOT) system Fig 7.</sentence>
    <sentence>Light-on-test (LOT) system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Defects can be repaired when identified.</sentence>
    <sentence>A typical repair system has a laser repair unit, tape grinding unit, color repair unit, and dry film repair unit (Ishikawa et al., 2005; Kim, 2007; Ning, Li, Lu, Li, &amp; Yao, 2003).</sentence>
    <sentence>For instance, a laser repair unit uses a solid-state 355/532 nm-wavelength laser to repair devices.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 8 shows a typical laser repair system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Repair system Fig 8.</sentence>
    <sentence>Repair system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Descriptive statistics of TFT-LCD project data The study company transformed itself into a high-tech company in the 1990s by specializing in developing TFT-LCD manufacturing and testing equipment.</sentence>
    <sentence>Despite its rapid business growth, management has paid little attention to the PMIS and project files were archived in various departments on paper or electronically.</sentence>
    <sentence>Although a PMIS are important to PMs, some problems exist (i.e., the extent to which a PMIS should be customized, and software efficacy, reliability, effort spent and the benefit/cost ratio) for most manufacturing-oriented companies using a PMIS.</sentence>
    <sentence>Additionally, experienced personnel often prevent mistakes by being reluctant to change from a familiar working environment.</sentence>
    <sentence>The data preprocessing stage consumed considerable time as the research team needed to acquire cost data and related parameters from manual documents, project files, and accounting information.</sentence>
    <sentence>For instance, geometrical and physical features of equipment were collected from the R&amp;D department; manufacturing process data were acquired from the product management department; client and order data were obtained from the business and marketing department; receivable and payment data were acquired from the finance and accounting department; contract and patent adoption issues were obtained from the legal department; and equipment layouts were acquired from the engineering and design department.</sentence>
    <sentence>Consequently, the company should store operational project data in a centralized data warehouse to archive project knowledge as a corporate asset and facilitate business intelligence discovery.</sentence>
    <sentence>Developing a model for estimation of TFT-LCD manufacturing equipment cost during early in the price quotation stage requires careful selection of features that have predictive relationships in the manufacturing process.</sentence>
    <sentence>These features must be identified based on equipment functions and characteristics (e.g., size, weight, shape, process, and equipment type); these features can be obtained easily from a client during the conceptual stage.</sentence>
    <sentence>Notably, quoted prices were not traceable in the study company, and only actual close-out cost data after equipment delivery were obtainable.</sentence>
    <sentence>A pilot analysis indicates that the explanatory power (R-square) and standard error of time-adjusted cost data compared with those of non-adjusted cost data is minimal.</sentence>
    <sentence>Equipment development costs were therefore not converted into base production year.</sentence>
    <sentence>Due to the accessibility and availability of project data, trade-offs were made while selecting factors for construction of subsequent models.</sentence>
    <sentence>After consulting experienced engineers and extracting product attributes from documents, the following candidate factors (Table 1) were determined as potential predictors (input) for preliminary cost estimates of TFT-LCD manufacturing equipment.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Parameters for TFT-LCD manufacturing equipment cost prediction.</sentence>
    <sentence>Parameter Min Max Mean ESIM Input variables Geometrical features</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Length of fabrication equipment (mm)&#9;1650&#9;5100&#9;3233.1&#9;X1"/>
  <section name="Width of fabrication equipment (mm)&#9;1000&#9;4200&#9;2220.7&#9;X2"/>
  <section name="Height of fabrication equipment (mm)&#9;1475&#9;29071&#9;2979&#9;X3"/>
  <section name="Weight of fabrication equipment (ton)&#9;0.3&#9;15&#9;3.7&#9;X4"/>
  <section name="Length of glass substrate (mm)&#9;538&#9;2500&#9;1266.6&#9;X5"/>
  <section name="Width of glass substrate (mm)&#9;316&#9;2200&#9;953.8&#9;X6">
    <sentence>Production characteristics</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Equipment development type&#9;(Repair, Macro, LOT)&#9;X7"/>
  <section name="Manufacturing process&#9;(TFT, CF, LCD, LCM)&#9;X8"/>
  <section name="Customer&#9;(CMO, AMTC, CPT, INNOLUX, TPO, AUO)&#9;X9"/>
  <section name="Order type&#9;(Old, New)&#9;X10"/>
  <section name="No. of patent&#9;0&#9;7&#9;2&#9;X11">
    <sentence>Financial planning</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="No. of order&#9;&#9;&#9;&#9;X12"/>
  <section name="Down payment&#9;&#9;&#9;&#9;X13"/>
  <section name="Payment condition&#9;&#9;&#9;&#9;X14">
    <sentence>Output variable Predicted cost (10,000 TWD) 198 1700 691.7 YESIM The project sample originally consisted of 519 TFT-LCD equipment development products delivered during 2005–2007.</sentence>
    <sentence>After aggregation of multiple orders from the same client, sample size was reduced to 129 projects and a derived variable, number of orders (NOOs), was created to account for the impact of multiple orders on quoted price.</sentence>
    <sentence>The geometrical features comprise the physical properties of fabrication equipment.</sentence>
    <sentence>The size range of glass substrate in product lines was 316 × 538(mm) to 2200 × 2500(mm).</sentence>
    <sentence>The LCD panel applications varied depending on the TFT-LCD products under production (e.g., monitors, TVs, portable PCs, e-books, and communication products).</sentence>
    <sentence>The production characteristics are fabrication equipment types—Macro, LOT, and Repair—and patents employed to fabricate these manufacturing machines.</sentence>
    <sentence>The manufacturing processes include those for TFTs, CFs, LCDs, and LCMs.</sentence>
    <sentence>A nominal variable represents customers placing orders.</sentence>
    <sentence>Some variables, such as payment conditions, were adopted to represent client financial planning.</sentence>
    <sentence>ESIM performance and prediction accuracy for Repair, Macro and LOT The historical cases were used as training sets based on equipment type (Table 2).</sentence>
    <sentence>Macro, LOT, and Repair prediction models were then trained, respectively Neter, Kutner, Nachtsheim, and Wasserman (1996) suggested that the best means of model testing is by collecting new data, enabling users to determine the applicability of a model to data beyond those on which the model is based (Neter et al., 1996).</sentence>
    <sentence>Thus, data for newly completed projects were randomly obtained upon verification of model training for test purposes.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Historical cases.</sentence>
    <sentence>Equipment type No.</sentence>
    <sentence>of training cases No.</sentence>
    <sentence>of testing cases Macro 44 7 LOT 35 4 Repair 50 5 In this study, mean absolute percentage error (MAPE) and root mean square error (RMSE) are evaluation criteria.</sentence>
    <sentence>The MAPE and RMSE are derived as follows: (1) (2) where n is the number of validation data, and Yi is equipment development cost.</sentence>
    <sentence>Accuracy measurements are taken using Eqs.</sentence>
    <sentence>(1) and (2) for both the training and test datasets.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 9 shows the Macro training results of difference between the predicted cost by the ESIM and actual cost.</sentence>
    <sentence>Macro equipment development cost is predicted by the ESIM with satisfactory accuracy.</sentence>
    <sentence>For the Macro system, the MAPE of the training dataset is 4.325% and the RMSE is 94.0577 (104 TWD), while the testing set is 11.617% and 76.5076 (104 TWD), respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 3 lists the specified C constant and γ value required as input patterns for the ESIM, along with individual prediction costs of test cases.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 10 shows the difference between predicted and actual costs for the test dataset.</sentence>
    <sentence>Macro training results Fig 9.</sentence>
    <sentence>Macro training results.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Macro results.</sentence>
    <sentence>Case no.</sentence>
    <sentence>ESIM predicted cost (104 TWD) Actual cost (104 TWD) Macro-1 445.74899 600 Macro-2 386.18947 340 Macro-3 359.94078 380 Macro-4 595.26459 498 Macro-5 454.92909 476.8 Macro-6 512.31947 580.79 Macro-7 504.64453 500.43 C, γ 198, 0.2122 RMSE (Training) 94.0577 (104 TWD) MAPE (Training) 4.325% RMSE (Testing) 76.5076 (104 TWD) MAPE (Testing) 11.617% Macro testing results Fig 10.</sentence>
    <sentence>Macro testing results.</sentence>
    <sentence>Similar analytical results are obtained for LOT and Repair system development cost predictions (Tables 4 and 5), while the LOT prediction has minimal MAPE and RMSE in training or test datasets.</sentence>
    <sentence>For the prediction performance via the MAPE, the LOT system is 3.427%, superior to Macro (11.617%) and Repair (5.658%) in terms of forecasting new cases.</sentence>
    <sentence>Figs.</sentence>
    <sentence>11–14 show the respective discrepancy figures for LOT and Repair systems.</sentence>
    <sentence>Generally, the overall MAPE of ESIM prediction performance is 4.525% for the training dataset of the Macro, LOT, and Repair systems.</sentence>
    <sentence>For new cases, the overall MAPE of test cases is 7.707%.</sentence>
    <sentence>The testing RMSE of each equipment are nearly comparable with the training RMSE.</sentence>
    <sentence>The overall performance measures implicitly support the verification of ESIM model (Tables 3–5).</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>LOT results.</sentence>
    <sentence>Case no.</sentence>
    <sentence>ESIM predicted cost (104 TWD) Actual cost (104 TWD) LOT-1 522.8365 509.964 LOT-2 552.2631 550 LOT-3 461.2885 430.346 LOT-4 514.2968 533.395 C, γ 0, 0.9997 RMSE (Training) 29.9609 (104 TWD) MAPE (Training) 2.464% RMSE (Testing) 19.3197 (104 TWD) MAPE (Testing) 3.427% Table 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>Repair results.</sentence>
    <sentence>Case no.</sentence>
    <sentence>ESIM predicted cost (104 TWD) Actual cost (104 TWD) Repair-1 1494.673 1500 Repair-2 1403.119 1312.5 Repair-3 1519.854 1600 Repair-4 1491.139 1612.85 Repair-5 1189.986 1300.17 C, γ 195, 0.1842 RMSE (Training) 88.6649 (104 TWD) MAPE (Training) 6.455% RMSE (Testing) 91.2335 (104 TWD) MAPE (Testing) 5.658% LOT training results Fig 11.</sentence>
    <sentence>LOT training results.</sentence>
    <sentence>LOT testing results Fig 12.</sentence>
    <sentence>LOT testing results.</sentence>
    <sentence>Repair training results Fig 13.</sentence>
    <sentence>Repair training results.</sentence>
    <sentence>Repair testing results Fig 14.</sentence>
    <sentence>Repair testing results.</sentence>
    <sentence>Furthermore, roughly 88% of the test cases have prediction errors &lt;13.59%.</sentence>
    <sentence>These prediction errors range at 0.355–25.708%.</sentence>
    <sentence>The analytical results show that the proposed ESIM approach outperforms the current analogous estimating procedure adopted in the TFT-LCD manufacturing equipment industry, which is 16.1% in general or worse based on the observations from the actual records and interviews with in-house project managers.</sentence>
    <sentence>On average, the proposed ESIM approach outperforms the current analogous estimation procedure by 52.1% for the test dataset.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Conclusions">
    <sentence>This study forecasts the costs of equipment used to fabricate TFT-LCDs using the novel ESIM.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ESIM is a hybrid intelligence technique integrating an SVM with an fmGA.</sentence>
    <sentence>The SVM primarily addresses learning and curve fitting by mapping input and output, and the fmGA primarily deals with global optimization concurrently while minimizing prediction error.</sentence>
    <sentence>The investigation demonstrates that the proposed ESIM can accurately predict the costs of TFT-LCD fabrication equipment (Marco, LOT, and Repair systems).</sentence>
    <sentence>Analytical results indicate that the overall MAPE is 4.525% for training datasets for the Macro, LOT, and Repair systems.</sentence>
    <sentence>For the randomly collected data for testing, the overall MAPE is 7.707%.</sentence>
    <sentence>Based on the performance measures, the proposed ESIM approach is adequate in predicting development prices of TFT-LCD equipment at early development stages as prediction error is within a satisfactory limit.</sentence>
    <sentence>The prediction performance using the ESIM is better than that of the current conventional analogous technique, achieving an average accuracy improvement of 52.1%.</sentence>
    <sentence>The strong global demand for TFT LCD panels is reflected in the multiple sizes available commercially.</sentence>
    <sentence>With experience, good judgment and timely adjustments, systematic knowledge discovery from sales records offers PMs of high-tech manufacturing equipment an effective and efficient way of estimating costs and quoting prices in the early stages of development for customers.</sentence>
    <sentence>Future work can focus on the development of a user-friendly computing system embedded with ESIM to help PMs acquire reference costs in a timely manner.</sentence>
  </section>
</article>
