<article>
  <title>Use of ARIMA mathematical analysis to model the implementation of expert system courses by means of free software OpenSim and Sloodle platforms in virtual university campuses</title>
  <abstract>
    <sentence>This paper describes the implementation of a virtual World based in GNU OpenSimulator.</sentence>
    <sentence>This program offers a great variety of Web 3.0 ways of work, as it makes possible to visit web sites using avatars created for that purpose.</sentence>
    <sentence>The Universities should be familiar with the creation of new metaverses.</sentence>
    <sentence>That is the reason why a new basic methodology for the creation of a course on expert systems within a metaverse in a virtual campus for e-learning.</sentence>
    <sentence>Besides the creation of a repository or island, it is necessary to make measurements of the performance of the server dedicated to host the system when the number of users of the application grows.</sentence>
    <sentence>In order to forecast the behavior of such servers, ARIMA based time series are used.</sentence>
    <sentence>The auto-correlogrames obtained are analyzed to formulate a statistical model, as close to reality as possible.</sentence>
  </abstract>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Expert systems</keyword>
    <keyword>Artificial intelligence</keyword>
    <keyword>OpenSim</keyword>
    <keyword>Sloodle</keyword>
    <keyword>ARIMA</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <section name="Introduction">
    <sentence>The e-learning project of the “Francisco José de Caldas” District University in Bogotá (Colombia) is currently on the first phase.</sentence>
    <sentence>The objective of the first phase is to learn about the use of virtual tools and their applications to carry out e-learning projects.</sentence>
    <sentence>Another goal is to overcome the difficulties associated with the use of appropriate visual interfaces and their adequate implementation.</sentence>
    <sentence>There is not much information at this moment about disadvantages that could impede the construction of a proper interface with the database and the LMS.</sentence>
    <sentence>The challenge lies in how to tackle new ways of presenting and visualizing contents, which it is something under much discussion nowadays, regarding which are the paths to keep us away from the static web that only allows the reading of documents, books and publications on cloud repositories.</sentence>
    <sentence>There are many teachers and institutions who claim to have better ways of accessing those new sources of information, in particular for the development of science courses on applied Artificial Intelligence.</sentence>
    <sentence>Thanks to globalization, improved internet speeds and global interconnection between networks, it is now feasible to access learning contents without the need of physical traveling, as the students can make use of these ITC resources no matter where they are.</sentence>
    <sentence>This shows the evolution from a static Web 2.0 to a dynamic Web 3.0.</sentence>
    <sentence>This change is made possible also by the development of simulators of virtual worlds such as Open Simulator (Fishwick, 2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>This simulator is created under the guidelines of SecondLife (by Linden Labs Linden Research) and it was released in 2007 and placed under the GPL (Barbulescu et al., 2011).</sentence>
    <sentence>This simulator is characterized by a modular structure written in C# and it supports multiple viewers such as the viewer Hippo OpenSim Viewer; RealXtend Viewer and the same SecondLife official viewer.</sentence>
    <sentence>Open Simulator complies with the client–server model.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the server the interconnected islands or rectangular regions are created, and the viewer is installed on the client.</sentence>
    <sentence>The viewer has similar functions as Mozilla Firefox or Google Chrome but they are used to access virtual worlds.</sentence>
    <sentence>The dynamism of Web 3.0 (Pattal, Li, &amp; Zeng, 2009) combines artificial intelligence techniques, geospatial mobility, interactivity, multimedia 3D, and the transformation towards a semantic database capable of learning.</sentence>
    <sentence>The combination of access to courses of expert systems and artificial intelligence on virtual worlds built with GNU tools besides the use of a statistical package is an excellent way to teach complex topics to students interested in them.</sentence>
    <sentence>Artificial intelligence is a science that deals with the design of computer systems that are capable of displaying characteristics that we associate with intelligence in human behavior: language comprehension, reasoning, learning and problem solving, among others.</sentence>
    <sentence>This has led to the emergence of numerous support tools for occupations, tasks and activities in a variety of areas.</sentence>
    <sentence>The virtual worlds have been no exception to that with the application of AI to many aspects of the benefits of digital virtual libraries, such as research, special papers, and knowledge management.</sentence>
    <sentence>Similarly, the vast amount of information emanating from student thesis and their teachers lends itself to input in databases for the extraction of embedded knowledge from the perspective of different forms of AI or its affiliated areas.</sentence>
    <sentence>This approach is contextualized within ITC development in Computer Sciences, some examples of which are systems databases and Storage Area Network SAN (Tate, Bernasconi, Mescher, &amp; Scholten, 2003).</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="3D Free tools to create a course in expert systems">
    <sentence>OpenSim 3D modeler OpenSim is a 3D application server that uses the same standards as SecondLife to communicate with their users.</sentence>
    <sentence>It emerges from the analysis of the structure of the source code viewer of SecondLife, released in early 2007 by Linden Labs under GPL, reverse engineered in order to create a 3D application server.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is characterized by being free software, it has a modular structure written in C# and it supports multiple viewers.</sentence>
    <sentence>To date OpenSim is on version 0.7.</sentence>
    <sentence>One of the biggest potentials of OpenSim is the ease with which a university can customize its development, design management systems, and integrate databases of LMS (Learning Management Systems) (Phankokkruad &amp; Woraratpanya, 2009) with OpenSim database, so that content can be created to suit the needs and methodologies of each institution (see Fig 1).</sentence>
    <sentence>View of an open virtual world simulator with geospatial database connectivity… Fig 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>View of an open virtual world simulator with geospatial database connectivity and information sharing in real time.</sentence>
    <sentence>OpenSim is used for designing, creating and easily implement 3D virtual worlds by many programmers around the world.</sentence>
    <sentence>Content targeted to different areas can be produced with this tool, such as e-learning, virtual tours, and simulations, amongst others.</sentence>
    <sentence>Moreover, being a free software tool, it enables low cost development and allows developers around the world to contribute to the development of new features.</sentence>
    <sentence>Moodle for a Web courses Moodle is an acronym for “Modular Object-Oriented Dynamic Learning Environment.” It is a software package for creating courses and web sites based on open source and developed in PHP.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is designed to work on different database engines specially MySQL (Di Giacomo, 2005), with the objective to help educators create and easily manage online learning communities.</sentence>
    <sentence>Moodle is designed to foster the building of knowledge for the student.</sentence>
    <sentence>Its first version was published in August 2002 and to date the current version is 2.2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Moodle currently has over 4.780,000 courses offered through 56,361 registered sites in 215 countries, including Colombia which is the eighth country in registered courses (see Table 1).</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>List of used tools with their descriptions.</sentence>
    <sentence>Tool Description OpenSimulator This software provides a platform on which the developer’s community can build virtual worlds that can be exchanged, learned, tested, analyzed, and improved through multi-institutional collaboration.</sentence>
    <sentence>The underlying software is written in ANSI C++, and the graphical user interface (GUI) is written in Java.</sentence>
    <sentence>PHP PHP is a server-side scripting language designed for web development Interface for OpenSimulator it allows grid citizens to create user accounts to access the metaverse grid.</sentence>
    <sentence>Grid owners can also manage all users for the grid, with a very powerful CMS system included.</sentence>
    <sentence>MySQL It is a GNU open source relational database management system (RDBMS).</sentence>
    <sentence>It is used to set StorageProvider and ConnectionString so that OpenSimulator can connect to a database.</sentence>
    <sentence>Sloodle It is an open source tool used to create a LMS base while developing at the same time their own supported solution for avatar classroom.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is similar to Moodle and allows the educator to set up individual learning exercises dynamically created and deleted on-demand for each student.</sentence>
    <sentence>Hippo viewer The Hippo OpenSim Viewer is a modified Second Life viewer, to access a virtual world.</sentence>
    <sentence>It allows the building up to a height of 10,000 m, scaling primes up to 256 × 256 × 256 m and other exciting features.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is run in Windows and Linux clients.</sentence>
    <sentence>Ubuntu server It is an open source operating system for 3D virtual world server.</sentence>
    <sentence>It allows multiple avatar users to custom build a virtual environment, and to interact with each other in real time.</sentence>
    <sentence>Sloodle project The project SLOODLE (Simulation Linked Object Oriented Dynamic Learning Environment) (Spaeth, Stuermer, Haefliger, &amp; Von Krogh, 2007) is a success code that integrates multi-user virtual environments like Second Life and OpenSim with the learning management platform Moodle.</sentence>
    <sentence>Sloodle provides a wide range of tools (some still in development) that enable virtual learning worlds and immersive education (Getchell, Miller, Nicoll, Sweetman, &amp; Allison, 2010; Lala &amp; Nishida, 2011).</sentence>
    <sentence>Such tools are fully integrated with a learning management system based on the web.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is already used by thousands of educators and students worldwide.</sentence>
    <sentence>Ubuntu operating server Ubuntu is an operating system that uses a Linux kernel and it is based on Debian (Spaeth et al., 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>It is maintained by the British firm Canonical and a developer community.</sentence>
    <sentence>This distribution is intended to improve the end user experience, making it easier to interact with the operating system through an improved GUI.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is one of the most popular distributions today with approximately 50% preference among Linux distributions.</sentence>
    <sentence>For the development of this project it should be noted that Linux is characterized as an operating system designed from the beginning as multithreaded, multiuser, and it manages the permissions for each user on processes and files from access by other users in a very secure way.</sentence>
    <sentence>Ubuntu comes by default, with the “root” user disabled, so that the system repeatedly would ask the user’s password to install any components and it is also known to be very careful with permissions at the time of modifying files and folders.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="OpenSim and virtual worlds">
    <sentence>To create a virtual course the following steps are to be carried out (Torres &amp; Uribe, 2012): 3.1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Installing XAMPP database It is necessary to have a web server to accommodate the contents of Moodle, and it is advisable to configure MySQL as the default database engine in the OpenSim server.</sentence>
    <sentence>We would need to use the XAMPP (Dvorski, 2007) Apache distribution which includes the installation of MySQL.</sentence>
    <sentence>Linux installation files for XAMPP are available on the official website of “Apache Friends”.</sentence>
    <sentence>Once the file has been downloaded, it should be decompressed under the “opt” file system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Finally the server must be started using the command “/opt/lampp/lampp start”.</sentence>
    <sentence>One of the utilities of XAMPP is the administration tool for MySQL databases from php: phpMyAdmin, which can be accessed from the home page of the server by typing http://localhost in a browser.</sentence>
    <sentence>The admin page does not have an enabled access control by default, so anyone with access to the server can change all the parameters.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is therefore recommended to set up access passwords.</sentence>
    <sentence>The XAMPP documentation describes how to do this.</sentence>
    <sentence>Installing the metaverse world with OpenSim On the download page are the OpenSim files needed for installation of the server.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is advisable to mount the server on a 32-bit version of Linux, since 64-bit versions often have compatibility issues with OpenSim and its dependencies.</sentence>
    <sentence>OpenSim was developed to run on the Microsoft dot NET framework and much of the code and scripts used in the metaverse are based on C#, so in order to install it on Linux it is required to install the Mono framework, which has the necessary libraries to compile those languages.</sentence>
    <sentence>The files needed to install Mono on Linux are in their official download page, they can be downloaded to the terminal with the installation commands too (e.g.</sentence>
    <sentence>Ubuntu: sudo apt-get install mono-complete).</sentence>
    <sentence>After having installed mono, the OpenSim file should be unzipped using the terminal.</sentence>
    <sentence>To start the server, the command “mono OpenSim.exe” should be entered with root permissions.</sentence>
    <sentence>If there are not any compatibility issues, the server should start.</sentence>
    <sentence>This loads all the necessary dependencies to the metaverse one by one.</sentence>
    <sentence>If this is the first time OpenSim is run on the computer, and if there is not any metaverse already created, then the simulator would request the creation of one, asking the information listed below: • New region name [ ]: alphanumeric characters.</sentence>
    <sentence>Name that will be given to the region.</sentence>
    <sentence>Enter the desired name for the region.</sentence>
    <sentence>• RegionUUID [UUID_by_default]: UUID.</sentence>
    <sentence>Unique identifier for this region.</sentence>
    <sentence>OpenSim proposes a default, so you could just press enter unless you prefer a specific UUID.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Region Location [1000.1000]: x, y coordinates.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is the desired coordinate point for the region.</sentence>
    <sentence>Mode must be specified for non-grid overlay on existing regions.</sentence>
    <sentence>Otherwise the default one can be accepted by pressing the enter key.</sentence>
    <sentence>• InternalAddress [0.0.0.0]: Wildcard Mask (IP address).</sentence>
    <sentence>This address is actually a wildcard mask that allows the owner to restrict the range of addresses that can access the server.</sentence>
    <sentence>In most cases it should be left to 0.0.0.0 by pressing enter, so that all hosts can access it.</sentence>
    <sentence>• InternalPort [5001]: # port (0-65535).</sentence>
    <sentence>Internal server port to be used for access.</sentence>
    <sentence>If port 5001 is not being used by other application, pressing the Enter key means accepting the default.</sentence>
    <sentence>• AllowAlternatePorts: True or False.</sentence>
    <sentence>Function still in the experimental stage.</sentence>
    <sentence>To be left false by pressing enter.</sentence>
    <sentence>• ExternalHostname: IP address.</sentence>
    <sentence>This is the address trough which clients will access the server, and it should take into account some considerations that are discussed later.</sentence>
    <sentence>To start it could be left as “SYSTEMIP”.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Do you wish to join an existing region to Udin state (yes/no)?</sentence>
    <sentence>[Yes]: This is used to attach the newly created region to an existing state, if there is a previously created state to which the administrator wants to join the region, and then the name you should be written.</sentence>
    <sentence>If there are not any states then by typing “no” it proceeds to create one.</sentence>
    <sentence>The parameters that are required to create one are: • State name [MyState]: alphanumeric characters.</sentence>
    <sentence>Any name.</sentence>
    <sentence>The following parameters should be remembered so that later on a new user can be created on the server, who will be the first user to access the state: • State owner first name [Test]: alphanumeric characters.</sentence>
    <sentence>The name to be used for the state owner.</sentence>
    <sentence>• State owner last name [User]: alphanumeric characters.</sentence>
    <sentence>The surname to be used for the estate owner.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Password: alphanumeric characters.</sentence>
    <sentence>User Password created.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Email [ ]: alphanumeric characters.</sentence>
    <sentence>Email user created.</sentence>
    <sentence>So now we have a region, a state and a user.</sentence>
    <sentence>With this ready, the server can be started.</sentence>
    <sentence>It can be accessed from any viewer.</sentence>
    <sentence>These parameters can be modified at any time by accessing the Regions.ini file located in the /bin/Regions folder of OpenSim.</sentence>
    <sentence>Building objects into OpenSim Creating and modifying objects in OpenSim are the basic operations for the construction of the metaverse.</sentence>
    <sentence>The first thing to do is to increase the size of the island.</sentence>
    <sentence>For this the command “terrain fill” and the desired number should be used.</sentence>
    <sentence>The region may have the maximum size of the grid, because if it is set to a larger size it would overlap with other regions in grid mode.</sentence>
    <sentence>Different tools inside OpenSim are (Gonzalez-Crespo, Rios-Aguilar, Ferro-Escobar, &amp; Torres, 2012): • Vision (Ctrl+1) is used to change the angle of view and the zoom of the camera.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Move (Ctrl+2): With this option the different objects in the region can be moved.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Edit (Ctrl+3): This is one of the most important tools; this tool changes easily the position, rotation and size of objects.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Create (Ctrl+4): This tool creates different basic objects like cubes, cylinders, cones, spheres, prisms, toroid and others.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Ground (Ctrl+5): With this tool the user can raise, level, smooth down or reset the selected field.</sentence>
    <sentence>Using this tool he or she can also change the properties to specific “plots”, including the type of texture that will be used to play the media (see Fig 2).</sentence>
    <sentence>OpenSim viewer and basic tools menu and tabs for designing courses in the… Fig 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>OpenSim viewer and basic tools menu and tabs for designing courses in the virtual worlds.</sentence>
    <sentence>When any of the above tools is opened, different tabs will appear at the bottom of the pop up window in which the user can make specific modifications in the created objects.</sentence>
    <sentence>The tabs available in the tools menu are: • General: Here the owner can make a description and edit the permissions and ownership of objects, and define the action performed by default when an avatar touches it.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Object: In this tab the user can set “physical” properties of the object in the metaverse, such as position, rotation, size, or even if the object is material, ghost, if it is locked, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>For some basic objects he can set additional options such as cross sections, start and end cuts, define whether it is or not hollow, and its twist, among others is.</sentence>
    <sentence>The detailed description of the management of client tools for building in OpenSim metaverse are not the subject of this document.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Features: It allows editing the characteristics associated with the physics engine simulator.</sentence>
    <sentence>OpenSim accepts different physics engines that allow more realistic simulations of objects, nevertheless for the purpose of this project they are not relevant.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Texture: Each object may also have different textures, which create more realistic environments and it is also used for playback of multimedia within the metaverse.</sentence>
    <sentence>The building of complex metaverse starts from basic objects and the time it takes to complete it will depend on the user ability to use the tools abovementioned.</sentence>
    <sentence>Connecting the new metaverse with Sloodle Once the administrator has the Moodle software and the Sloodle tools running, its functions can be used directly into the metaverse.</sentence>
    <sentence>For this course we installed Moodle on the same server of OpenSim, and then we linked the Sloodle set located on the client host with the Sloodle Controller located in the server.</sentence>
    <sentence>The steps to carry out this are as follows: • Step 1: Click on the Sloodle set.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Step 2: Write in the chat the Moodle site address, for example http://localhost/moodle or http://192.168.1.100:5001/moodle.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Step 3: A dialog box appears in the viewfinder.</sentence>
    <sentence>Then click on “Go to page”.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Step 4: To authorize Sloodle objects, a browser should be opened, which could be the one included in the viewer or the default browser of the operating system.</sentence>
    <sentence>The owner should log in with admin role or teacher of the course in which the controller was added, and then she should authorize it by selecting the previously controller added to Moodle, and then she should send the form.</sentence>
    <sentence>After this she could close the browser.</sentence>
    <sentence>This should be done only once for the main controller of the Sloodle set, and once for each object added to the metaverse.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Step 5: Finally the adminsitrator should click again on the Sloodle Set, and then click on Download configuration, so that the object that was authorized may have access to the specified Moodle platform (see Fig 3).</sentence>
    <sentence>Flow-chart to create a virtual course with Sloodle in the OpenSim Fig 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Flow-chart to create a virtual course with Sloodle in the OpenSim.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Why to teach an expert systems 3D virtual course?">
    <sentence>There is still much work to be done about the programming of artificial intelligence, and the development of robots and smart machines.</sentence>
    <sentence>There is a great need of algorithms and software related to this important area of knowledge.</sentence>
    <sentence>That is an important reason for the universities to offfer courses that promote the study of those techniques and other topics regarding autonomous systems that could be capable of reasoning similarly to the human brain (Giarratano &amp; Ricley, 1998).</sentence>
    <sentence>Benefits of using OpenSim 3D virtual worlds in educational courses • The teachers may cooperate with students on a less formal basis, and students can choose an individual learning program and establish cooperation with other students.</sentence>
    <sentence>• The course can be followed many times without having to be created again and again.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Students can create avatars according to their taste and with the features they feel like.</sentence>
    <sentence>• The course can create graphical objects that simulate the behavior of a hypothetical system with artificial intelligence.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Virtual worlds have similar tools as the Web 2.0 for creating, sharing and transfer of new knowledge by using chats, forums, wiki, e-mail, video conference and other tools.</sentence>
    <sentence>• It promotes the use of ICT to promote the grow of new developments in the area of computer and telecommunications systems.</sentence>
    <sentence>The expert system course contains the following chapters Buckley and Eslami (2002), Russell and Norvig (2002) Chapter 1 Introduction: • Knowledge-acquisition interface • User interface • Knowledge base • Inference engine Knowledge-acquisition interface The knowledge-acquisition interface controls how the expert and knowledge engineer interact with the program to incorporate knowledge into the knowledge base.</sentence>
    <sentence>It includes features to assist experts in expressing their knowledge in a form suitable for reasoning by the computer.</sentence>
    <sentence>User interface The user interface is the part of the program that interacts with the user.</sentence>
    <sentence>It prompts the user for information required to solve a problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>It displays conclusions and explains its reasoning.</sentence>
    <sentence>Knowledge base The knowledge base consists of specific pieces of knowledge about some substantive domain.</sentence>
    <sentence>A knowledge base differs from a data base in that the knowledge base includes both explicit knowledge and implicit knowledge.</sentence>
    <sentence>The knowledge bases can contain many different types of knowledge together with the process of acquiring knowledge into the knowledge base.</sentence>
    <sentence>Inference engine The inference engine uses general rules of inference to reason from the contents of the knowledge base and draw conclusions which are not already explicitly stated, but can be inferred from the knowledge base.</sentence>
    <sentence>Inference engines are capable of symbolic reasoning, not just mathematical reasoning.</sentence>
    <sentence>Hence, they expand the scope of fruitful applications of computer programs.</sentence>
    <sentence>The specific forms of inference permitted by different inference engines vary, depending on several factors, including the knowledge representation strategies employed by the expert system.</sentence>
    <sentence>The course on expert systems presents many visions about knowledge management: • Explicit knowledge • Implicit knowledge • Domain knowledge • Common sense or world knowledge • Heuristics • Algorithms knowledge • Procedural knowledge • Declarative or semantic knowledge • Public knowledge • Private knowledge • Shallow knowledge • Deep knowledge • Meta-knowledge Chapter 2: Understanding the expert systems: • Sample applications.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Tools for development expert systems.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Software for building, maintaining, and compiling rule sets.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Potential benefits to use expert systems.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Evolution and new applications.</sentence>
    <sentence>Chapter 3: Rules for Reasoning: • Premises to conclusions.</sentence>
    <sentence>o IF, Then.</sentence>
    <sentence>o Boolean.</sentence>
    <sentence>o Conjunction, disjunction.</sentence>
    <sentence>o Exclusive OR.</sentence>
    <sentence>o Input actions.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Managing Rules.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Reasoning with Rules.</sentence>
    <sentence>Chapter 4: Introduction to other applications: • Data mining.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Fuzzy logic.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Simulation models.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Neural networks.</sentence>
    <sentence>Chapter 5: On line problems: • Solved problems.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Exercises proposed.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Sharing new knowledge.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Discussions and feedback.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Course evaluation.</sentence>
    <sentence>• New applied research.</sentence>
    <sentence>• References.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Conclusion.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Example of an expert system in a virtual world">
    <sentence>The use of digital libraries changed over the years and the more so with the advent of internet.</sentence>
    <sentence>From that moment the way knowledge is accessed has changed because in cyberspace there are countless sources of information that comes in many formats like text, video and many more.</sentence>
    <sentence>The change is so important that new generations of students prefer to search the web before they go to a university; this arises the need for more innovative spaces that encourage these students, youth and adults to enter virtual worlds and visit these new courses of interaction and new models of access to knowledge (see Fig 4).</sentence>
    <sentence>Overview about the welcome screen to the course of expert systems in the OpeSim… Fig 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>Overview about the welcome screen to the course of expert systems in the OpeSim 3D virtual world created.</sentence>
    <sentence>The fundaments for the creation of effective hardware and software for expert systems begin by understanding how to use expert systems tools and then by applying the acquired knowledge to solve real problems.</sentence>
    <sentence>Such intelligent systems must be composed of sensors, actuators, and algorithms that make correct decisions based on rules and that use intelligent Web access protocols to search for knowledge.</sentence>
    <sentence>This is achieved by using Web-based architectures, OWL, XML (Hannes &amp; Soren, 2005; Isaza, Castillo, López, &amp; Castillo, 2009, Ontologies (Brewster, 2004; Isaza, Castillo, López, Castillo, &amp; López, 2010), Semantic Services of presentation RDF (Czajkoeski et al., 1997; Simons et al., 2004) type, data management, Grid repositories (Erdmann, Fensel, Horrocks, Klein, &amp; Melnik, 2008), XAMPP compatible databases, connection to external sources of scientific data, social, geographic and more.</sentence>
    <sentence>All this can be arranged by using Service Oriented Architectures (SOA).</sentence>
    <sentence>It is necessary to involve researchers in several scientific fields such as engineers, software developers, university students, research groups in network architecture and a community of architects and 3D designers of metaverse and courses similar to those exposed in this paper.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is important as well to have access to high speed Internet, grid computing and SOA services.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Traffic and experimental evaluation in ARIMA mathematical model">
    <sentence>In this first phase of development the system performed measurements of traffic of 25 users who entered the 3D virtual world.</sentence>
    <sentence>The samples were extracted from the learning system and then they were included in the ARIMA (Cottrell &amp; Lucchetti, 2008) mathematical model as a class of stochastic processes used to analyze time series according due to Box and Jenkins model: (1) The server used for testing had as operating system Linux CentOS 6.3, with hardware that was designed with a processing capacity of 16 cores each, with a processing speed of 2.93 GHz, Dell board, RAM of 8 × 2048 MB DDR3-1333 MHz and a DD-HDD space about 73 GB.</sentence>
    <sentence>The GNU software used to create the mathematical model is GRETL (GNU Regression Econometric and Time-Series Library) (GNU Force).</sentence>
    <sentence>This tool generates statistical analysis by means of correlograms and first and second derivatives to produce a stationary function in order to predict the behavior of a larger number of users vs. the CPU speed in MHz.</sentence>
    <sentence>These series present high frequency, no constant mean and variance, and multiple seasonality.</sentence>
    <sentence>The Table 2 data, are represented in the following GRETL graphic (see Fig 5): Table 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Number of user, CPU percent utilization and real speed variation tested in a 3D virtual world course.</sentence>
    <sentence>User CPU utilization (%) Variation (%) Speed CPU (MHz) Variation (MHz) 1 4.2 0 162.3 0 2 6.4 2.2 208.2 45.9 3 10.9 4.5 297.2 89 4 14 3.1 378.7 81.5 5 16 2 427.4 48.7 6 21.3 2.5 587.79 68.25 7 24.6 3.3 668.37 80.58 8 25.9 1.3 736.98 68.61 9 28.3 2.4 809.73 72.75 10 31.2 2.9 888.75 79.02 11 33.7 2.5 966.21 77.46 12 36.3 2.6 1011.23 45.02 13 37.1 0.8 1080.33 69.1 14 39.5 2.4 1134.27 53.94 15 42.2 2.7 1201.97 67.7 16 45.1 2.9 1284.66 82.69 17 47.4 2.3 1362.65 80.99 18 49.3 1.9 1409.02 43.37 19 52.4 3.1 1455.49 46.47 20 55.2 2.8 1536.55 81.06 21 58.1 2.9 1599.3 62.75 22 60.5 2.4 1678.4 79.1 23 63.2 2.7 1759.37 80.97 24 65.6 2.4 1812.78 53.41 25 67.3 1.7 1900.47 87.79 Average 36.712 2.427 1033.872 66.853 Time series original function in GRETL Fig 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>Time series original function in GRETL.</sentence>
    <sentence>After analyzing the statistical behavior is necessary to take the first difference as shown in the following figure (see Fig 6): Plot time series function and his first derivate Fig 6.</sentence>
    <sentence>Plot time series function and his first derivate.</sentence>
    <sentence>This difference gives the graph of its Correlogram, which has 1 ACF point and 2PACF points (see Fig 7).</sentence>
    <sentence>Correlogram time series function ACP and PACF Fig 7.</sentence>
    <sentence>Correlogram time series function ACP and PACF.</sentence>
    <sentence>To perform this observation, samples of 20 users crews were taken where 80% and 20% are left to perform the prediction (see Fig 8): ACF and PACF values Fig 8.</sentence>
    <sentence>ACF and PACF values.</sentence>
    <sentence>According to the coefficients obtained from the autocorrelation functions and the partial autocorrelation prediction models, which were based on the coefficients p (Rho) AR(1) = −0,4498, q1 q2 MA(1) = −0,4498, and q2 MA(2) = −0,4079, the ARIMA model combination ARIMA(1,1,1) were defined with this equation: (2) From the data provided in Fig 9 the function prediction plot for 23 samples, the differentiated function is painted in red and the corresponding forecast as follows (see Fig 10): Model I ARIMA (1,1,1) function evaluation Fig 9.</sentence>
    <sentence>Model I ARIMA (1,1,1) function evaluation.</sentence>
    <sentence>Graph ARIMA model 1 Forecast prediction Fig 10.</sentence>
    <sentence>Graph ARIMA model 1 Forecast prediction.</sentence>
    <sentence>The Fig 11 presents the exact data for the differentiated function and data for function prediction also calculated the RMSE (Root Mean Square Error): Model I ARIMA (1,1,2) function evaluation (1) Fig 11.</sentence>
    <sentence>Model I ARIMA (1,1,2) function evaluation (1).</sentence>
    <sentence>From the data provided in Figs.</sentence>
    <sentence>11 and 12 function prediction plot for 23 samples in red differentiated function is presented in red and the corresponding forecast (see Fig 13): Model I ARIMA (1,1,2) function evaluation (2) Fig 12.</sentence>
    <sentence>Model I ARIMA (1,1,2) function evaluation (2).</sentence>
    <sentence>Graph ARIMA model 2 Forecast prediction Fig 13.</sentence>
    <sentence>Graph ARIMA model 2 Forecast prediction.</sentence>
    <sentence>The Fig 14 presents the exact data for the differentiated function and the data for function prediction calculated the RMSE (Root Mean Square Error) too: Function prediction calculated the RMSE (Root Mean Square Error) Fig 14.</sentence>
    <sentence>Function prediction calculated the RMSE (Root Mean Square Error).</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Results">
    <sentence>The first step in creating an expert system course in a virtual world is to learn the different tools available for this purpose and how the same function can be properly used without generating errors at the moment of building these courses.</sentence>
    <sentence>The main difficulty found was to operate correctly, because virtual worlds had problems connecting to more than 25 viewers or students represented by their avatars (see Fig 15).</sentence>
    <sentence>Screen where there are several students with their avatars taking the course of… Fig 15.</sentence>
    <sentence>Screen where there are several students with their avatars taking the course of expert systems using Sloodle presenter for the ARIMA model.</sentence>
    <sentence>There is also within the metaverse a course linked to the Moodle platform which is installed on the same Ubuntu server.</sentence>
    <sentence>In this platform test elements were created which were accessed from the course (see Fig 16).</sentence>
    <sentence>Implementation of testing methodology for the ARIMA mathematical (GNU Force) Fig 16.</sentence>
    <sentence>Implementation of testing methodology for the ARIMA mathematical (GNU Force).</sentence>
    <sentence>The ARIMA models in (1) and (2) have been applied to predict the behavior in terms of CPU server speed of the number of avatar access to the virtual 3D course, The Fig 8 corresponds to the Autocorrelation function for ACF AR(1), PACF MA(1,2), The first model ARIMA(1,1,1) for 23 samples shows mean errors around 5% (this prediction appears in Fig 11), for the second model ARIMA(1,1,2) presents mean errors around 8%.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Conclusion">
    <sentence>This paper analyzes the implementation of a metaverse targeted to educational virtual environments and the dissemination of scientific knowledge in the form of free open expert system courses.</sentence>
    <sentence>A simulation was carried out by means of GNU tools that control the characteristics of the objects created.</sentence>
    <sentence>It was motivated by the need experienced by different research groups of several Universities to study the utilization of free tools to set up science courses.</sentence>
    <sentence>In particular it has been shown how the application of OpenSim in specific areas of study in engineering has already made significant progress.</sentence>
    <sentence>A good example of application of these tools is the development of a expert system course with the aim of testing and proofing ARIMA mathematical models of behavior when the server has a high load of traffic generated by access of students who may wish to take the online courses.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ARIMA model produces an acceptable medium term forecast.</sentence>
  </section>
</article>
