<article>
  <title>A macro-economic model to forecast remittances based on Monte-Carlo simulation and artificial intelligence</title>
  <abstract>
    <sentence>A computer system based on Monte-Carlo simulation and fuzzy logic has been designed, developed and tested to: (i) identify covariates that influence remittances received in a specific country and (ii) explain their behavior throughout the time span involved.</sentence>
    <sentence>The resulting remittance model was designed theoretically, identifying the variables which determined remittances and their dependence relationships, and then developed into a computer cluster.</sentence>
    <sentence>This model aims to be global and is useful for assessing the long term evolution of remittances in scenarios where a rich country is the host (United States of America) while a poor country is the where the migrant is from (El Salvador).</sentence>
    <sentence>By changing the socio-economic characteristics of the countries involved, experts can analyze new socio-economic frameworks to obtain useful conclusions for decision-making processes involving development and sustainability.</sentence>
  </abstract>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Bayesian networks</keyword>
    <keyword>Monte Carlo simulation</keyword>
    <keyword>Fuzzy logic</keyword>
    <keyword>Remittances</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <section name="Introduction">
    <sentence>Monte-Carlo simulation has been widely used to model complex systems in economy.</sentence>
    <sentence>These models let researchers evaluate the evolution of socio-economic variables, like remittances, in uncertain environments (Kydlandl, 2006; Stern, 1997).</sentence>
    <sentence>Input variables in Monte-Carlo are random variables whose behavior depends on their corresponding statistical distributions (Fishman, 1996; García-Alonso &amp; Pérez-Alcalá, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>When there are not enough raw data, the expert-based selection of these statistical distributions (StD) is critical to determine the expected outputs (Kuhl, Lada, Steiger, Wagner, &amp; Wilson, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>Monte-Carlo simulation models are completely blind.</sentence>
    <sentence>This means that it is very complicated to make them understand complex dependence relationships (DR) among covariates.</sentence>
    <sentence>Bayesian network models (Barreiros &amp; Vargas, 1998) are appropriate methodological approaches for understanding causal-based DR when they exist.</sentence>
    <sentence>When these DR are algebra-based, they can easily be included in a simulation engine (Fishman, 1996).</sentence>
    <sentence>However, when they are expert-based (causal rules) – experts agree that they exist but it is very difficult to make them explicit because the absence of data or its bad quality, only artificial intelligence models can be used to incorporate them into a simulation engine (García-Alonso, 2008; Liu, Yue, Su, &amp; Yao, 2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>A fuzzy inference engine was designed to evaluate expert-based DR (García-Alonso, 2008; Gegov, 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>This engine designs appropriate fuzzy rules automatically once the input values have been determined by the simulation engine according to expert-based prerequisites (Cox, 2005; Fishman, 1996; Stern, 1997).</sentence>
    <sentence>These rules determine the values of the analyzed variable – the output of the fuzzy inference engine – (García-Alonso, 2008) that produce a stochastic distribution because: (i) the input variables are stochastic and (ii) the interaction among input variables produces random effects.</sentence>
    <sentence>The aim of this paper is to design and develop a remittance assessment model based on Monte-Carlo simulation and fuzzy logic to forecast the evolution of this variable throughout time comparing specific North–South economies.</sentence>
    <sentence>This model evaluates the relationships between socio-economic variables in uncertainty conditions modeled in a Bayesian network.</sentence>
    <sentence>The resulting model has been checked by considering United States of America (USA)–El Salvador remittance flows.</sentence>
    <sentence>Remittances, mainly in poor countries, are one of the critical elements for economic development.</sentence>
    <sentence>They have been defined as the current transfers made by migrants who live and are employed in other economies.</sentence>
    <sentence>From a simplified point of view, migrants are those workers who move to an economy different from their origins and remain there, or are expected to stay a year or longer (Amuedo-Dorantes &amp; Mazzolari, 2010; International Monetary Fund – IMF, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>In 2008 officially recorded remittances at international level were formally estimated at $397,047 million per year, and have undergone a great increase in recent years from the $2049 million per year in 1970 (World Bank, 2010).</sentence>
    <sentence>Remittances are of increasing scientific interest because they are much more stable over time than private capital flows and exports, which makes them a very attractive source of foreign financing for poor countries (Wu &amp; Zeng, 2010).</sentence>
    <sentence>In addition, remittances are unrequited transfers of capital that, unlike other capital flow, do not create future obligations (Chami et al., 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>In poor countries, the total amount of remittances is greater than the amount of direct foreign investment, portfolio flows from financial markets and official development assistance (Amuedo-Dorantes &amp; Mazzolari, 2010).</sentence>
    <sentence>These facts suggest that the macroeconomic effects of remittances have relevant implications for policy makers in these countries (Chami et al., 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>Borjas (2008) considered that wages abroad depend on a socio-economic vector that describes the structure of the host countries, the number of years that migrant workers live in the host country, the age of workers in the year analyzed and, finally, when they arrived in the host country.</sentence>
    <sentence>His microeconomic model of individual choice established that people decide to migrate depending on a cost-benefit relationship that involves (Borjas, 2008; Todaro, 1989) the differential of wages between the country of origin and the host country (Gandolfo, 1998), the unemployment differential and, finally, the initial investment needed, including transport costs, language, religion, culture, nationality requisites, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>A potential migrant decides then to migrate if, according to his skills, he expects to obtain a measurable profit.</sentence>
    <sentence>The New Economy of Migration (Massey et al., 1998) also includes host country benefits as another variable to estimate the number of migrants.</sentence>
    <sentence>The existence of social networks in the host country is also highlighted in the Social Capital Theory (Massey &amp; Emilio, 1994) while the Segmented Labor Market Theory (Piore, 1979) explains international migration as an answer to the permanent demand for immigrant labor that is inherent to the economic structure of developed nations.</sentence>
    <sentence>The propensity of the migrant population to remit wages back home is the third variable to explain remittances.</sentence>
    <sentence>According to Adams (2008), this variable is a function of the migrant’s profile and skills, the number of years living in the host country and the income of the family at home.</sentence>
    <sentence>The differential of interest rates was included by Chami et al.</sentence>
    <sentence>(2008) as another relevant variable.</sentence>
    <sentence>Higgins, Hysenbegasi, and Pozo (2004) and Freund and Spatafora (2008) include transmission costs, exchange rates and the social stability of the country of origin in their analysis of migrant propensity to remit wages back home.</sentence>
    <sentence>Finally, Lueth and Ruiz-Arranz (2006) also suggest that higher inflation in the home country increases remittance flows to compensate the loss of purchasing power.</sentence>
    <sentence>This paper is structured as follows: first, the North–South Remittance model is developed theoretically and then the dependence relationship modeling is described.</sentence>
    <sentence>In section three the resulting model is applied to the situation involving the USA and El Salvador.</sentence>
    <sentence>Some relevant results are then described in section four and, finally, a brief discussion of relevant issues concludes this paper.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="The Bayesian network: modeling remittances">
    <sentence>The North–South Remittance Model (NSRM) includes three main variables considered outlets in a Bayesian network (Fig 1(a)): wages received from abroad (Wxt), the migrant population (Nemt) and the propensity to remit wages (Rwt), being t the time.</sentence>
    <sentence>Bayesian networks: (a) conceptual model and (b) time-based model Fig 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Bayesian networks: (a) conceptual model and (b) time-based model.</sentence>
    <sentence>Remittances (1) have been defined as transfers made by migrants who are employed and have lived (at least one year) in other economies (IMF (International Monetary Fund), 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>(1) Tret being the remittances received in the home country in year t according to specific migrant skills i (i = 1) low-skilled – less than 8 years of schooling, i = 2 medium-skilled – 9–12 years of schooling – and i = 3 highly-skilled – 13 years or over of schooling.</sentence>
    <sentence>Docquier and Marfouk (2005) and the ways of sending the remittances k (k = 1 formal and k = 2 informal).</sentence>
    <sentence>Rwikt is the corresponding propensity to remit wages, Wxikt are the wages earned abroad and, finally, Nemikt is the migrant population in each collective.</sentence>
    <sentence>Wages abroad Wxikt are the average monetary units earned by each migrant collective in the host country (2); this variable defines the first dependence relationship (DR) in the model because the algebraic structure of the function (Borjas, 2008) is not yet defined: (2) being Secikt the socio-economic characteristics of the environment in t. This variable summarizes the average labor market framework and has been defined in a [0, 100] range where 0 means very poor labor market conditions and 100 means very favorable conditions.</sentence>
    <sentence>Yrikt is the average number of years that the migrant collective remains in the host country.</sentence>
    <sentence>Finally, the employability Emikt includes all the characteristics of the migrant collective on average – skills, schooling, labor experience, language proficiency, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>This variable is also defined within a [0, 100] range where 0 means possessing very poor skills and 100 means very highly skilled.</sentence>
    <sentence>Migrant population Nemikt(3) is the number of people in each collective who have migrated and stayed in the host country in the year t: (3) where Mpikt is the propensity to migrate (percentage) and Ntikt the population of the collective in the home country in t. The NSRM defines Mpikt(4) as another DR: (4) Wdikt being the differential (times) wages on average (Borjas, 2008; Todaro, 1989) in t, Wuikt the average differential (times) unemployment rates (Todaro, 1989), Inikt the average initial investment – within a [0, 100] range (0 means no investment needed and 100 means financially impossible), Hsbikt, the host country social benefits (differential) on average compared to those in the home country and, finally, Esikt shows the difference (scale) in potential economic growth between the two countries.</sentence>
    <sentence>The last input in (1) is the propensity to remit wages Rwikt(5), which is another DR: (5) being Skikt the average migrant skills (scale) in t. This variable includes years of schooling, academic level, migrants’ experience and the labor orientation of workers.</sentence>
    <sentence>In addition to this variable (5) also includes: Agikt which is the average migrant age; Hmfikt which describes the average family structure (scale) in the home country; Hsfikt the average family (scale) in the host country; and Idikt the average nominal interest rate differential (times).</sentence>
    <sentence>Other variables included in (5) are: Tcikt transaction costs (scale) on average – the cost of sending money; Sstikt the average socio-political stability (scale) of the home country; Mdikt the average duration (Dustmann &amp; Mestres, 2010) of the migration (years) and Pppikt the average purchasing power parity (times) – the relation between the price differential and the exchange rate differential.</sentence>
    <sentence>This structure (Fig 1(a)) defines a standard Bayesian network (Directed Acyclic Graph) that varies throughout the time span (Fig 1(b)): (6) being V the whole set of variables and paikt the Makovian parents of each specific variable xikt.</sentence>
    <sentence>The joint probability function (6) cannot be easily calculated due to the existence of (2), (4) and (5).</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Dependence relationship evaluation">
    <sentence>The NSRM can be considered to be a generalized fuzzy model because it manages two uncertainty sources: stochastic ones (the values of the variables considered inputs in DR are obtained according to their StD by Monte-Carlo simulation) and relational ones (variables which are considered outputs in DR are evaluated, knowing the input values, using fuzzy logic – type I sets).</sentence>
    <sentence>This approach is used instead of the generalized regression model due to a lack of data series and the fact that the reliability or accuracy of existing data is suspect.</sentence>
    <sentence>Therefore, the model presented in this paper uses a new approach to forecasting when expert knowledge is accessible and input data is known or can be estimated using, for example, Monte-Carlo simulation (García-Alonso, Arenas-Arroyo, &amp; Pérez-Alcalá, 2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>This model is based on the expert-based interpretation of DR (García-Alonso, 2008) which can be described in semantic terms using standard IF … THEN rules.</sentence>
    <sentence>Expert knowledge can be used to define complex DR when it is impossible to design algebraic equations due to the lack of poor quality of data (Fishman, 1996; García-Alonso, 2008; Stern, 1997).</sentence>
    <sentence>In order to incorporate explicit expert knowledge into a computer system, DR must be translated into formal language that is accessible to both experts and the computer (Russel &amp; Norvig, 2003).</sentence>
    <sentence>The model structure includes a prior knowledge base that approximates the analytical behavior of the real system (Gupta &amp; Sharma, 2004).</sentence>
    <sentence>As defined above, a DR is a structure that relates inputs to produce outputs following a logical reasoning process based on standard IF … THEN rules.</sentence>
    <sentence>According to this, a DR is made up of many rules that define a fuzzy system (García-Alonso, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>For example, (2) is a DR where Wxikt is the output that is determined once the values of Secikt, Yrikt and Emikt – inputs – have been estimated using a Monte-Carlo simulation engine (García-Alonso, 2008; García-Alonso et al., 2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>Rather than numerical values, fuzzy inference manages semantic terms translated into linguistic labels, called Membership Functions (MF).</sentence>
    <sentence>According to this procedure (Gegov, 2007), input values have to be fuzzified (translated to semantic terms) first and then these semantic terms identify what corresponds to the output which is, in turn, defuzzified (translated to a numerical value, the result).</sentence>
    <sentence>The structure of a fuzzy rule in a specific DR like (2) can be described as: (7) where linguistic labels like HIGH are the MF or fuzzy sets (Cox, 2005).</sentence>
    <sentence>Specific combinations of input MF define the output MF when the corresponding rule exists in the prior knowledge base.</sentence>
    <sentence>In order to make the input evaluation systematic and the rule design automatic, input variables have to be described by the expert (García-Alonso, 2008; García-Alonso et al., 2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>This includes their feasible ranges, their variation throughout the time span (increasing, decreasing, constant, following a specific tendency, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>), their orientation (positive: the greater the input value, the greater the output value or, on the other hand, negative: the greater the input value, the lower the output value); and, finally, their weights on the output.</sentence>
    <sentence>The number of rules in each DR is a very important drawback as it is the result of an exponential function of the number of inputs (Cordon, Herrera, &amp; Zwir, 2003).</sentence>
    <sentence>(8) d being the number of DR, p the number of MF and m the number of inputs.</sentence>
    <sentence>In order to solve this problem, the inference engine automatically designs and evaluates fuzzy rules only when needed (more details can be found in García-Alonso, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>This process needs the description of all DR including: inputs and outputs, the DR type (Q) which takes control of MF output (MF0) displacements and the DR intensity (D) which evaluates fulfillment nuances on fuzzy rules (García-Alonso, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>Using this information, each input MF combination (MFi, i = 1, 2, … , m) defines the MF0.</sentence>
    <sentence>(9) wi (i = 1, 2, …, m) as they are the input weights on the output (their relative relevance).</sentence>
    <sentence>According to García-Alonso (2008), the first step in this process is calculating the input values using the Monte-Carlo simulation engine.</sentence>
    <sentence>Secondly, these input values are fuzzified automatically.</sentence>
    <sentence>In this step all the input MF (MFi) and their corresponding membership degrees are determined depending on both the input values and the MF shape selected (triangular and Z functions).</sentence>
    <sentence>Then, MF0 is determined using (9), taking into consideration that there is only one MF0 for each combination without repetition of MFi.</sentence>
    <sentence>Finally, the fuzzy inference engine uses the product-sum-gravity with-superposition method (Cox, 2005) to evaluate the final value of the output.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="United States of America–El Salvador remittance model">
    <sentence>The North–South Remittance Model (NSRM) designed has been used to study the case of El Salvador.</sentence>
    <sentence>This case is a very good example for three reasons: (i) most El Salvador migrants – 91% – are in the USA; (ii) there is no bias in the variables defined as differentials – the percentage of migrants is about 16% of the total population of El Salvador (World Bank, 2010) – which implies that everyone has almost-perfect information about the conditions of the investment needed to migrate; (iii) remittances are a very important part of the financial flow in El Salvador and they keep its economic activity stable at 18% of its Gross Domestic Product.</sentence>
    <sentence>The USA dollar became the currency in El Salvador in 2001.</sentence>
    <sentence>This fact produced a significant reduction in purchasing power and has produced an increase in migration in recent years (CEPAL, 2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>Furthermore, the hurricane in 1998 and two earthquakes in 2001 have made people more and more dependent on remittances (McGraw &amp; Wong, 1996).</sentence>
    <sentence>As a result of dollarization, El Salvador’s interest rate has declined but is still higher (about 7% in 2007) than its counterpart in USA.</sentence>
    <sentence>The characteristics of NSRM variables (Table 1 and Fig 2) describe El Salvador’s socio-economic situation throughout the time span and compare it to that in the USA (Encuesta de Hogares y Propósitos Múltiples, 2010; Ministerio de Economía.</sentence>
    <sentence>El Salvador, 2010; Ministerio de Trabajo y Previsión Social, 2010; Restrepo, 2004; US Department of Labor, 2010).</sentence>
    <sentence>For the purpose of simplification, these variables have not taken into consideration either migrant skills i or their ways of sending money k. Table 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Expert-based structure of input variables (t is the year analyzed).</sentence>
    <sentence>Time Variation1 Value ranges2 Rate of growth (time interval and rate, %) From To Sect Decreasing U[78, 80] U[60, 62] Constant with fluctuations3 Yrt Increasing U[0.1, 4] U[36, 40] Constant with fluctuations Emt Increasing U[20, 23] U[47, 50] Constant with fluctuations Wdt Fluctuating U[7.5, 8] U[8.5, 9] 1–7: 0.0; 8–10: 1.4; end: −2.8 Wut Fluctuating U[4.7, 5] U[2.7, 2] 1–10: 0.0; end: −1.0 Int Fluctuating U[52.5, 55] U[32.5, 30] 1–20: −0.9; 21–90: −0.25; end: −0.05 Hsbt Fluctuating U[4.1, 4.2] U[3.1, 3] 1–7: 0.0; 8–10: 1.0; end: −1.3 Est Fluctuating U[55, 57.5] U[77.5, 80] 1–10: 1; 11–14: 1.3; end: −2 Ntt Fluctuating U[47, 50] U[77, 80] 1–20: 1.2; 21–80: 0.25; end: 0.05 Skt Increasing U[10, 13] U[37, 40] Constant with fluctuations Agt Constant TR[18, 22, 32, 36] Small fluctuations admitted Hmft Fluctuating U[50, 54] U[86, 90] 1–9: 0.01; 10–13: 0.75; end: −0.5 Hsft Fluctuating U[10, 12] U[28, 30] 1–9: 0.01; 10–13: 0.75; end: −0.5 Idt Constant U[2, 5] Small fluctuations admitted Tct Decreasing U[14, 15] U[5, 6] Constant with fluctuations Sstt Constant T[10, 40, 50] Small fluctuations admitted Mdt Constant TR[10, 25, 34, 60] Small fluctuations admitted Pppt Constant U[2, 4] Small fluctuations admitted 1 Variation throughout the time span.</sentence>
    <sentence>2 Statistical distributions.</sentence>
    <sentence>U: Uniform; T: Triangular; TR: Trapezoidal.</sentence>
    <sentence>3 Fluctuations calculated at random on the estimated valued et: .</sentence>
    <sentence>Evolution throughout the time span of some selected input (Emt, Wut, Hsbt and… Fig 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Evolution throughout the time span of some selected input (Emt, Wut, Hsbt and Idt) means and confidence intervals (1995–2019).</sentence>
    <sentence>For all the fuzzy rules which structure the DR (Table 2), the probability of occurrence (that the fuzzy rule be instantiated) is 0.98.</sentence>
    <sentence>If the fuzzy rule is not instantiated, the output value is calculated by the Monte-Carlo engine according to the StD selected for it (Table 2).</sentence>
    <sentence>Nuances – random distortion – in rule fulfillment are considered, including centered-increasing intensity (García-Alonso, 2008) which means: the more centered the input values, the truer the rule (D = 0).</sentence>
    <sentence>Fuzzy rules are true (instantiated without any distortion, D = 0) at least 40% of the simulations.</sentence>
    <sentence>The characteristics of the corresponding DR inputs described in Table 3 show how decisive the differences in labor conditions between the two countries are.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Characteristics of the dependence relationships: outputs and structure (t is the year analyzed).</sentence>
    <sentence>Units Probability of occurrence1 StD2 Q Intensity3 Rules considered true (%)4 Wxt $ per person 0.98 U[7500, 18000] +3 Centered-increasing 40.0 Rwt Percentage 0.98 U[15, 20] −4 Centered-increasing 40.0 Mpt Percentage 0.98 U[10, 20] +3 Centered-increasing 40.0 1 The fuzzy inference engine is activated with these probabilities.</sentence>
    <sentence>If the fuzzy inference engine is not activated then the Monte-Carlo simulation engine calculates the output value according to the statistical distribution (StD) selected.</sentence>
    <sentence>2 Statistical distribution (StD) selected for the output when the fuzzy rules are not instantiated.</sentence>
    <sentence>U: Uniform statistical distribution.</sentence>
    <sentence>3 Centered-increasing: the more centered the input values, the truer the rules (if the rule is completely true then D = 0 and the membership function for the output is not distorted at all).</sentence>
    <sentence>4 Minimum percentage of rules that are always considered true and, therefore, the membership function of the output is not distorted: D = 0.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Description of dependence relationship (DR) inputs.</sentence>
    <sentence>Units DR1 Weight Orientation2 Sect Scale [0, 100] (2) 0.1500 Positive Yrt Years (2) 0.1000 Positive Emt Scale [0, 100] (2) 0.7500 Positive Wdt Times (4) 0.3500 Positive Wut Times (4) 0.2900 Positive Int Scale [0, 100] (4) 0.1500 Negative Hsbt Differential (4) 0.0200 Positive Est Scale [0, 100] (4) 0.0250 Positive Ntt Scale [0, 100] (4) 0.1650 Positive Skt Scale [0, 100] (5) 0.0400 Negative Agt Years (5) 0.0400 Negative Hmft Scale [0, 100] (5) 0.4000 Positive Hsft Scale [0, 100] (5) 0.4000 Positive Idt Times (5) 0.0001 Positive Tct Scale [0, 100] (5) 0.0500 Negative Sstt Scale [0, 100] (5) 0.0200 Negative Mdt Years (5) 0.0500 Negative Pppt Times (5) 0.0001 Positive 1 Dependence relationship formula in the text.</sentence>
    <sentence>2 Influence on the output.</sentence>
    <sentence>Positive: the greater the input value, the greater the output value.</sentence>
    <sentence>Negative: the greater the input value, the lower the output value.</sentence>
    <sentence>The number of simulations chosen was 10,000 (10 batches of 1000 simulations each).</sentence>
    <sentence>Results obtained in each replication were compared to the real data available.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Results">
    <sentence>The values for the variables obtained summarized the socio-economic situation in El Salvador as compared to the USA between 1995 and 2014 (Table 4).</sentence>
    <sentence>These values evaluated the remittances Tret received each year by the former country.</sentence>
    <sentence>In this time period, four intervals were highlighted (Fig 3): (i) from 1995 to 1999, the “pre-dollarization” period, in which remittances increased from $1.1 B US to almost $1.4 B US, although at the end of this period two earthquakes destroyed huge zones in El Salvador; (ii) from 2000 to 2006, the “dollarization” period, when remittances reached approximately $3.5 B US; (iii) 2007 and 2008, the “crisis” period in which remittance growth decelerated; and (iv) 2009–2014 where there was a forecast of results.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>Basic statistics for remittances (millions) and wages abroad (US $/person) in some critical years.</sentence>
    <sentence>Year (t) Remittances (Tret) CI3 Wages abroad1 (Wxt) Mean σ2 MQE2 GM σ2 1995 1419.52 97.31 12639.72 [1408.52, 1430.53] 11061.66 388.17 2000 1715.92 65.68 240.88 [1708.49, 1723.35] 11643.02 321.00 2005 2978.67 169.38 263.47 [2959.51, 2997.83] 12051.79 137.10 2010 4270.46 520.77 Forecasted 12406.09 131.76 1 There is no historical data, so the statistical error cannot be calculated.</sentence>
    <sentence>2 Mean Quadratic Error: simulated values vs. real values.</sentence>
    <sentence>3 Confidence interval.</sentence>
    <sentence>Output (Wxt, Rwt, Mpt and Tret) simulated values (continuous lines) versus real… Fig 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Output (Wxt, Rwt, Mpt and Tret) simulated values (continuous lines) versus real values (break lines) in El Salvador: historical data and projections (1995–2014).</sentence>
    <sentence>The simulated values for Wxt, Rwt, MPt and Tret adjusted the tendency of the real values (Fig 3).</sentence>
    <sentence>The model fits the “dollarization period” almost perfectly and tends to overestimate the periods pertaining to “pre-dollarization” and the “crisis”.</sentence>
    <sentence>This behavior is the result of the difficulty entailed in the fine-tuning of parameters for all the StD, this fact is evident in adjusting Mpt (Fig 3).</sentence>
    <sentence>From 1995 to 1999 Tret simulated values on average are greater than real remittances (in 1995–1997 between 29% and 38% and in 1998–1999, 19% approximately).</sentence>
    <sentence>This difference is close to the variations observed in Mpt (Fig 3) as well as the percentage of informal capital flow estimated by Freund and Spatafora (2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>Moreover, the propensity to send money using informal channels could be greater than normal because of the shock waves that the El Salvador economy experienced as a result of the “Tequila crisis” in Mexico (1995–1996), the fall of real wages in 1996–1997 (CEPAL, 2009) and hurricane Mitch in 1998 which could have resulted in a decrease in the migrants’ confidence in formal channels (Table 5).</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>Basic statistics for the propensity to migrate (%) and the propensity to remit wages (%) in some critical years.</sentence>
    <sentence>Year (t) Propensity to migrate (Mpt) Propensity to remit wages (Rwt) Mean σ2 MQE GM σ2 MQE 1995 12.34 0.00598 0.33 19.11 0.0012 2000 12.99 0.00039 0.64 19.12 0.0028 −0.87 2005 15.24 0.00034 −1.34 25.00 0.0031 3.00 2010 15.86 0.00047 30.60 0.0107 In the third period, the model overestimates Tret.</sentence>
    <sentence>Nevertheless, it correctly estimated the slope change that took place between 2006 and 2008 – remittance growth rates decreased by 12%.</sentence>
    <sentence>This variation was reproduced by the simulation model although a bit displaced in time.</sentence>
    <sentence>The reduction in the Hispanic employment rate in the USA was probably the main reason for this change in tendency.</sentence>
    <sentence>The difference between simulated and real values in this period cannot be explained by informal dispatch of capital because the competence of formal channels had increased in recent years.</sentence>
    <sentence>As of 2009 a moderate and slow increase in the Hispanic employment rate in the USA is expected in the fourth period.</sentence>
    <sentence>Remittances to El Salvador will not reproduce the same evolution as that observed in the “dollarization” period (World Bank, 2010).</sentence>
    <sentence>The more or less stable, probably increasing, Tret evolution is expected till 2014 (Fig 3).</sentence>
    <sentence>The analysis of average remittance growth rates (Fig 4) is very revealing.</sentence>
    <sentence>Our simulation model does not match these estimators except in the second period and globally in the third.</sentence>
    <sentence>The first one is very conflictive mainly because of the extreme rate increase in 2000.</sentence>
    <sentence>In this year, the dollarization process was in process and migrants sent more money due to the favorable currency exchange situation.</sentence>
    <sentence>Our model does not predict sudden economic impacts but does absorb their consequences and appropriately readjust their results throughout the time span (Figs.</sentence>
    <sentence>3 and 4).</sentence>
    <sentence>Rates of growth of the remittances (year 2000 showed exceptional behavior) Fig 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>Rates of growth of the remittances (year 2000 showed exceptional behavior).</sentence>
    <sentence>An Intraclass Correlation Analysis (McGraw &amp; Wong, 1996) was carried out (α = 0.05) to check the agreement rate between average simulated results and real remittances received by El Salvador.</sentence>
    <sentence>Intraclass Correlation Coefficients (ICC) were classified using the nominal scale proposed for the kappa index by Landis and Koch (1977) and show (Table 6) that the correlation between simulated and real scores can be considered “almost-perfect” when dealing with remittance values that are: “fair to moderate” if differentials ( ) are taken into account, but only “slight” if rates of growth ( ) are compared.</sentence>
    <sentence>Removing the year 2000 from the analysis, the ICC improves to the status of “moderate” when differentials are considered and to “slight-to-moderate” when rates of growth are compared.</sentence>
    <sentence>These results confirm that this year can be considered an exception to the rule.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 6.</sentence>
    <sentence>Intraclass correlation coefficients.</sentence>
    <sentence>From 1995 to 2008 Idem excluding the year 2000 Remittances Differentials Rates Remittances Differentials Rates Individual 0.945 0.538 0.212 0.943 0.617 0.358 Mean 0.972 0.699 0.350 0.971 0.763 0.527</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Conclusion">
    <sentence>The NSRM allows us to determine the statistical evolution of remittances during a time span even when data series are missing and/or are not reliable enough.</sentence>
    <sentence>Furthermore, in uncertain situations, our methodology (simulation and fuzzy logic) offers the possibility to study the model’s sensitivity to any input variations when standard econometric models cannot be used due to a lack of statistical data.</sentence>
    <sentence>In these circumstances, only expert knowledge can be used to approximate real environments but the results obtained have to be validated using secondary data.</sentence>
    <sentence>This trial and error procedure can be very complicated, although not impossible, when databases are incomplete.</sentence>
    <sentence>Taking into account the USA–El Salvador remittance framework, NSRM results are very sensitive to the “a priori” selection of input StD and their evolution throughout the time span (these StD are time-dependent).</sentence>
    <sentence>This selection depends on experts’ criteria, which are always based on existing macroeconomic models.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the countries where remittances are critical for their economies, natural disasters – earthquakes and hurricanes – as well as socio-economic shocks – dollarization and financial crisis – usually play a relevant role with significant consequences for the population.</sentence>
    <sentence>The NSRM can be adjusted to understand these phenomena once they have occurred or, on the other hand, to forecast their economic effects before they occur.</sentence>
    <sentence>Nevertheless, results have shown that extreme impacts on the economy cannot be predicted easily even when their medium-long term consequences have been estimated almost perfectly.</sentence>
    <sentence>By hybridizing existing macroeconomic models our NSRM can interpret the overall implications of both variable values and environmental changes.</sentence>
    <sentence>The separate treatment of variables and their relationships allows us to analyze the model’s sensitivity to numerical or statistical variations throughout the time span which makes it a useful tool to aid decision-making.</sentence>
    <sentence>This model can be used to evaluate more complicated socio-economic environments (more than only one migrant collective, different host countries, different ways of sending money, etc.)</sentence>
    <sentence>combining new variables from different sources whether economic, sociological, or of other kinds.</sentence>
  </section>
</article>
