<article>
  <title>Dynamic economic load dispatch using hybrid swarm intelligence based harmony search algorithm</title>
  <abstract>
    <sentence>This paper presents the hybrid harmony search algorithm with swarm intelligence (HHS) to solve the dynamic economic load dispatch problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>Harmony Search (HS) is a recently developed derivative-free, meta-heuristic optimization algorithm, which draws inspiration from the musical process of searching for a perfect state of harmony.</sentence>
    <sentence>This work is an attempt to hybridize the HS algorithm with the powerful population based algorithm PSO for a better convergence of the proposed algorithm.</sentence>
    <sentence>The main aim of dynamic economic load dispatch problem is to find out the optimal generation schedule of the generators corresponding to the most economical operating point of the system over the considered timing horizon.</sentence>
    <sentence>The proposed algorithm also takes care of different constraints like power balance, ramp rate limits and generation limits by using penalty function method.</sentence>
    <sentence>Simulations were performed over various standard test systems with 5 units, 10 units and 30 units and a comparative study is carried out with other recently reported results.</sentence>
    <sentence>The findings affirmed the robustness and proficiency of the proposed methodology over other existing techniques.</sentence>
  </abstract>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Harmony search</keyword>
    <keyword>Particle swarm optimization</keyword>
    <keyword>Dynamic load dispatch</keyword>
    <keyword>Transmission losses</keyword>
    <keyword>Ramp rate limit</keyword>
    <keyword>Valve point loading</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <section name="Introduction">
    <sentence>Dynamic economic dispatch (DED) is one of the major optimization problems in power system operation (Wood &amp; Wollenberg, 1984).</sentence>
    <sentence>It is used to determine the optimal combination of power outputs of all generating units to minimize the total cost of fuel over the entire scheduling periods.</sentence>
    <sentence>Also, the constraints imposed on system operation by generator ramping rate limits have to be considered.</sentence>
    <sentence>Traditionally, the cost function for each generator has been approximately represented by a single quadratic function and the valve-point effects due to the presence of multiple steam admitting valves were ignored in the DED problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>This would not replicate the practical system and often lead to inaccuracy in the resulting dispatch.</sentence>
    <sentence>The DED problem with valve-point effects is represented as a non-smooth optimization problem having complicated and non-convex characteristics.</sentence>
    <sentence>Besides it is difficult to solve because of its large dimensionality.</sentence>
    <sentence>Various methods have been applied to solve the DED problem in the past decades.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, all those methods may not be able to give an optimal solution and, may get stuck at local optima.</sentence>
    <sentence>The major methods include quadratic programming (Ross &amp; Kim, 1980), dynamic programming (Travers &amp; Kaye, 1998) and lagrangian relaxation approach (Hindi &amp; Ab Ghani, 1991).</sentence>
    <sentence>These methods were facing problems in obtaining optimal solution due to the nonlinear and non-convex fuel cost characteristics of generating units.</sentence>
    <sentence>The computational drawbacks of existing derivative-based numerical methods have forced the researchers all over the globe to rely on metaheuristic algorithms founded on simulations to solve engineering optimization problems.</sentence>
    <sentence>A common factor shared by the metaheuristics is that they combine rules and randomness to imitate some natural phenomena.</sentence>
    <sentence>Last few decades have seen an incredible growth in the field of nature-inspired meta-heuristics.</sentence>
    <sentence>Two families of algorithms that primarily constitute this field today are the evolutionary algorithms (EAs) (Back, Fogel, &amp; Michalewicz, 1997; Fogel, 2000; Goldberg, 1989) and the swarm intelligence (SI) algorithms (Engelbrecht, 2006; Kennedy, Eberhart, &amp; Shi, Swarm Intelligence, 2001).</sentence>
    <sentence>The solution of static economic dispatch is solved by genetic algorithm in Bakirtzis, Petridis, and Kazarlis (1994) and Walters and Sheble (1993) and particle swarm optimization (Gaing, 2003).</sentence>
    <sentence>The DELD problem with non smooth cost function is solved by using hybrid evolutionary programming and sequential quadratic programming method in Attaviriyanupap, Kita, Tanaka, and Hasegawa (2002), deterministically guided particle swarm optimization in Victoire and Jeyakumar (2005a), hybrid particle swarm optimization with sequential quadratic programming in Victoire and Jeyakumar (2005b), modified hybrid EP-SQP in Victoire and Jeyakumar (2005c), simulated annealing in Panigrahi, Chattopadhyay, Chakrabarti, and Basu (2006), adaptive particle swarm optimization in Panigrahi, Ravikumar Pandi, and Das (2008), differential evolution in Balamurugan and Subramanian (2008), modified differential evolution in Yuan et al.</sentence>
    <sentence>(2008), improved particle swarm optimization in Yuan, AnjunSu, Yuan, Nie, and Wang (2009) and hybrid differential evolution method in Yuan, Wang, Yuan, Zhang, and Yuan (2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>However choosing control parameters for all these evolutionary based algorithms are much difficult task.</sentence>
    <sentence>In 2001, Geem et al.</sentence>
    <sentence>proposed harmony search (HS) (Geem, 2009; Geem, Kim, &amp; Loganathan, 2001; Lee &amp; Geem, 2004a), a derivative-free, metaheuristic algorithm, mimicking the improvisation process of music players.</sentence>
    <sentence>Since its inception, HS has successfully been applied to a wide variety of practical optimization problems like pipe-network design (Geem, Kim, &amp; Loganathan, 2002), structural optimization (Lee &amp; Geem, 2004b), vehicle routing (Geem, Lee, &amp; Park, 2005), combined heat and power economic dispatch (Vasebi, Fesanghary, &amp; Bathaeea, 2007), and scheduling of multiple dam system (Geem, 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>HS may be viewed as a simple real-coded genetic algorithm (GA) (Back et al., 1997; Goldberg, 1989), since it incorporates many important features of GA like mutation, recombination, and selection.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, on complex and multi-modal fitness landscapes, the performance of HS is not free from false/premature convergence.</sentence>
    <sentence>In order to overcome these drawbacks, several modifications are introduced such as improved harmony search algorithm (Mahdavi, Fesanghary, &amp; Damangir, 2007), global-best harmony search (Omran &amp; Mahdavi, 2008), and hybrid harmony search algorithm with sequential quadratic programming (Fesanghary, Mahdavi, Minary-Jolandan, &amp; Alizadeh, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>This article describes a new variant of HS that synergistically incorporates some features of another very powerful optimization algorithm in current use, well-known as the particle swarm optimization (PSO) algorithm (Eberhart &amp; Shi, 1998, 2001; Kennedy &amp; Eberhart, 1995) into classical HS with a view of improving the accuracy, convergence speed, and robustness of the latter.</sentence>
    <sentence>Hybridization of intelligent systems is a promising research field of modern artificial intelligence (AI) concerned with the development of the next generation of intelligent systems.</sentence>
    <sentence>A fundamental stimulus to the investigations of hybrid intelligent systems (HIS) is the awareness in the academic communities that combined and integrated approaches will be necessary if the remaining tough problems in AI are to be solved.</sentence>
    <sentence>Recently, HIS are becoming popular due to their capabilities in handling many real world complex problems, involving imprecision, uncertainty and vagueness, high-dimensionality (Grosan, Abraham, &amp; Ishibuchi, 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>In recent years it has become evident that a skilled combination of a met heuristic with other optimization techniques, a so called hybrid met heuristic, can provide a more efficient behavior and a higher flexibility.</sentence>
    <sentence>Here we apply the proposed hybrid swarm intelligence based harmony search (HHS) algorithm to solve dynamic economic load dispatch (DELD) problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>Note that an earlier attempt to incorporate the ideas of gbest PSO model into HS can be traced in the work of Omran and Mahdavi (2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>The proposed approach, called global-best harmony search (GHS) (Omran &amp; Mahdavi, 2008), modifies the pitch-adjustment step of the HS such that the new harmony can mimic the best harmony in the harmony memory thus, replacing the band width (bw) parameter altogether and adding a social dimension to HS.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, as will be evident, our hybridization scheme differs significantly from their approach.</sentence>
    <sentence>Specifically, in our algorithm, the pitch adjustment phase of HS is accomplished via an adaptive PSO where a particle with high fitness moves slowly as compared to a particle with small fitness (Ravikumar Pandi &amp; Panigrahi, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>This is achieved by varying the inertia factor between an upper limit and a lower limit.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Problem formulation">
    <sentence>The objective function corresponding to the production cost can be approximated to be a quadratic function of the active power outputs from the generating units.</sentence>
    <sentence>Symbolically, it is represented as (1) (2) is the expression for cost function corresponding to ith generating unit and ai, bi and ci are its cost coefficients, Pit is the real power output (MW) of ith generator corresponding to time period t, NG is the number of online generating units to be dispatched, T is the total time period of dispatch.</sentence>
    <sentence>The cost function for unit with valve point loading effect is calculated by using (3) where, ei and fi are the cost coefficients corresponding to valve point loading effect.</sentence>
    <sentence>Due to the valve point loading the solution may be trapped in the local minima and it also increases the nonlinearity in the system.</sentence>
    <sentence>This constrained DELD problem is subjected to a variety of constraints depending upon assumptions and practical implications.</sentence>
    <sentence>These include power balance constraints to take into account the energy balance; ramp rate limits to incorporate dynamic nature of DELD problem and prohibited operating zones.</sentence>
    <sentence>These constraints are discussed as under.</sentence>
    <sentence>Power balance constraints or demand constraints This constraint is based on the principle of equilibrium between total system generation and total system loads (PD) and losses (PL).</sentence>
    <sentence>That is, (4) where PLt is obtained using B-coefficients, given by (5) 2.2.</sentence>
    <sentence>The generator constraints The output power of each generating unit has a lower and upper bound so that it lies in between these bounds.</sentence>
    <sentence>This constraint is represented by a pair of inequality constraints as follows: (6) where, and are lower and upper bounds for power outputs of the ith generating unit in MW.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ramp rate limits Under practical circumstances ramp rate limit restricts the operating range of all the online units for adjusting the generator operation between two operating periods.</sentence>
    <sentence>The generation may increase or decrease with corresponding upper and downward ramp rate limits.</sentence>
    <sentence>So, units are constrained due to these ramp rate limits as mentioned below.</sentence>
    <sentence>(7) (8) where is the power generation of unit i at previous hour and URi and DRi are the upper and lower ramp rate limits respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>The inclusion of ramp rate limits modifies the generator operation constraints (6) as follows: (9) 2.4.</sentence>
    <sentence>Formulation of fitness function To evaluate the fitness of each individual in the population in order to minimize the fuel costs while satisfying unit and system constraints, the following fitness-function model is adopted for simulation in this article: (10) where λ1 and λr are penalty parameters.</sentence>
    <sentence>The penalty term reflects the violation of the equality constraint and assigns a high cost of penalty function.</sentence>
    <sentence>The Prlim is defined by (11)</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Hybrid swarm Intelligence based harmony algorithm">
    <sentence>Harmony search is a new meta-heuristic optimization algorithm which imitates the music improvisation process applied by musicians.</sentence>
    <sentence>Each musician improvises the pitches of his/her instrument to obtain a better state of harmony.</sentence>
    <sentence>The goal of the process is to reach a perfect state of harmony.</sentence>
    <sentence>The following section describes classical harmony search algorithm and its variants.</sentence>
    <sentence>Classical harmony search algorithm The different steps of the HS algorithm are described below: • Step 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>The 1st step is to specify the problem and initialize the parameter values.</sentence>
    <sentence>The optimization problem is defined as minimize (or maximize) f (x) such that , where f (x) is the objective function, x is a solution vector consisting of N decision variables (xi) and and are the lower and upper bounds of each decision variable, respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>The parameters of the HS algorithm i.e.</sentence>
    <sentence>the harmony memory size (HMS), or the number of solution vectors in the harmony memory; harmony memory considering rate (HMCR); pitch adjusting rate (PAR); and the number of improvisations (NI) or stopping criterion are also specified in this step.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Step 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>The 2nd step is to initialize the harmony memory.</sentence>
    <sentence>The initial harmony memory is generated from a uniform distribution in the ranges , where 1 ⩽ i ⩽ N. This is done as follows: • Step 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>The third step is known as the ‘improvisation’ step.</sentence>
    <sentence>Generating a new harmony is called ‘improvisation’.</sentence>
    <sentence>The new harmony vector is generated using the following rules: memory consideration, pitch adjustment, and random selection.</sentence>
    <sentence>The procedure works as follows: Pseudo-code of improvisation in HS for each i ϵ [1, N] do ifU(0, 1) ⩽ HMCRthen /∗memory consideration∗/ begin , where j U(1, 2, … , HMS).</sentence>
    <sentence>ifU(0, 1) ⩽ PARthen /∗ Pitch adjustment ∗/ begin , where r U(0, 1) and bw is the arbitrary distance bandwidth parameter else /∗ random selection ∗/ endif done • Step 4: In this step the harmony memory is updated.</sentence>
    <sentence>The generated harmony vector replaces the worst harmony in the HM (harmony memory), only if its fitness (measured in terms of the objective function) is better than the worst harmony.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Step 5: The stopping criterion (generally the number of iterations) is checked.</sentence>
    <sentence>If it is satisfied, computation is terminated.</sentence>
    <sentence>Otherwise, Steps 3 and 4 are repeated.</sentence>
    <sentence>Improvement in harmony search (IHS) algorithm Improvement in harmony search (IHS) algorithm is proposed in Omran and Mahdavi (2008) by dynamically varying pitch adjustment rate (PAR) values with generation number as expressed as (12) where PAR-Pitch adjustment rate for each generation; PARMin – minimum pitch adjusting rate; PARMax – maximum pitch adjusting rate; NI – number of generations; gn – generation number.</sentence>
    <sentence>Proposed hybrid swarm intelligence based harmony search (HHS) algorithm The improvement of dynamically varying the PAR values is adopted in this work to make more effective in classical harmony search algorithm.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the pitch adjustment step of classical HS, each vector is given a random perturbation of maximum magnitude ± bw, where bw is a control parameter of the algorithm, called distance bandwidth.</sentence>
    <sentence>Here instead of going for an arbitrary distance bandwidth or dynamically varied bandwidth by logarithmic function based on generation number (Omran &amp; Mahdavi, 2008), we perturb each trial solution vector using the concepts of an adaptive PSO.</sentence>
    <sentence>Since, the stability of convergence of particle swarm optimization algorithm is well explained and a plethora of successful research works have been reported on the improvement of PSO (for a comprehensive review, see (Banks, Vincent, &amp; Anyakoha, 2007; Valle, Venayagamoorthy, Mohagheghi, Hernandez, &amp; Harley, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>In the particle swarm optimization the movement of particle is determined by velocity in the particular generation.</sentence>
    <sentence>The position of a particle is influenced by the best position found so far by itself (i.e.</sentence>
    <sentence>its own experience) and the position of the best particle in the swarm (i.e.</sentence>
    <sentence>the experience of swarm).</sentence>
    <sentence>Here instead of the classical PSO, the particle position is adjusted such that the highly fitted particle (best particle) moves slowly when compared to the low fitted particle (Ravikumar Pandi &amp; Panigrahi, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>This preserves the good locations (nearer to the global optima) on the search space from random perturbation and is conceptually similar to the mechanism of elitism incorporated in many EAs to preserve the fittest chromosomes across the generations.</sentence>
    <sentence>This can be achieved by selecting different ω values for each particle according to their rank, between ωmin and ωmax as in the following form: (13) The adaptation of the inertia factor in this way helps the swarm to converge faster to globally optimal solution, than classical PSO.</sentence>
    <sentence>The complete pseudo-code of the algorithm is presented below: Pseudo-code of improvisation in HHS for each i ϵ [1, N] do ifU(0, 1) ⩽ HMCRthen /∗memory consideration∗/ begin ifU(0, 1) ⩽ PAR(gn) then /∗Pitch adjustment∗/ begin else /∗random selection∗/ endif done Where ωmin and ωmax is choosen as 0.1 and 0.8. is the velocity of ith particle in the current generation.</sentence>
    <sentence>is the particle position in the current generation.</sentence>
    <sentence>C1 and C2 are cognitive and social co-efficient having the values 2.1 as used by classical PSO algorithm and r1–r4 are the random numbers generated between [0, 1].</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Results and discussion">
    <sentence>In this paper three different cases are considered to demonstrate the performance and applicability of the proposed algorithm.</sentence>
    <sentence>In case 1, a five unit system with transmission losses and non smooth cost characteristics is considered.</sentence>
    <sentence>In case 2, a 10 unit system having non smooth cost characteristics is considered.</sentence>
    <sentence>In case 3, a 10 unit system is tripled to obtain 30 unit systems.</sentence>
    <sentence>The proposed algorithm has been implemented in Matlab 7.4 on an IBM PC with 2 GHz core2duo processor and 2 GB RAM.</sentence>
    <sentence>A result obtained by proposed method is given in following sections.</sentence>
    <sentence>Case 1: five unit system In this case the five unit system data such as cost co-efficient, Bmn loss co-efficient, ramp rate limits, power generation limits and load demand are taken from Balamurugan and Subramanian (2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>The dynamic scheduling problem is considered for 24 interval of the day.</sentence>
    <sentence>The algorithm parameters are selected after conducting many experiments in the wide range to obtain the best fuel cost value, and finally considered values of parameters are population = 50, no of iteration = 1000, c1 = 2.1, c2 = 2.1, HMCR = 0.95, PPAR = 0.9 − 0.4.</sentence>
    <sentence>The simulation is performed for 25 trials and the obtained best optimum power generation value of all five generators in the 24 h scheduling horizon is given in Table 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>The average computational time taken for the proposed method is 2.8 min, whereas the time taken by DE (Balamurugan &amp; Subramanian, 2008) is reported as 5.14 min.</sentence>
    <sentence>The power loss for this optimum schedule is 196.66 MW.</sentence>
    <sentence>The comparison of results obtained by proposed method with other reported results in the literature such as SA (Panigrahi et al., 2006), APSO (Panigrahi et al., 2008) and DE (Balamurugan &amp; Subramanian, 2008) is given in Table 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>The comparison of convergence rate for the proposed algorithm with classical harmony search technique is depicted in Fig 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>The result obtained by proposed method guarantees that the better solution is reached when compared to other reported results in the literature.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Result of 24 h DED for five unit system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Load hours Pg1 Pg2 Pg3 Pg4 Pg5 1 10.00 20.00 30.00 124.5153 229.5196 2 19.0579 20 30.0553 140.8022 229.5196 3 10.00 20.00 30.00 190.8022 229.5535 4 10.00 20.00 67.0193 209.8158 229.5196 5 10.00 20.00 95.5324 209.7941 229.5196 6 13.9438 50.00 112.6735 209.8158 229.5196 7 10.00 72.4568 112.6735 209.8158 229.5196 8 12.6852 98.5553 112.6735 209.8158 229.5196 9 42.6852 105.4231 112.7472 209.8158 229.5196 10 64.0073 98.5398 112.6735 209.8158 229.5196 11 75.00 104.0275 112.6735 209.8158 229.5196 12 75.00 124.6537 112.6735 209.8158 229.5668 13 64.0074 98.5398 112.6735 209.8158 229.5196 14 49.6001 98.5568 112.6735 209.8158 229.5196 15 47.4275 98.5398 112.6735 174.9201 229.5196 16 21.4844 98.5398 112.6735 124.9201 229.573 17 10.00 87.6105 112.6735 124.9079 229.5196 18 10.0234 98.5398 112.6735 165.1878 229.5196 19 12.7024 98.5398 112.6735 209.8158 229.5196 20 42.6534 119.9291 112.6735 209.8158 229.5755 21 39.3487 98.5398 112.6735 209.8158 229.5196 22 10.00 98.5398 112.6735 162.134 229.5196 23 10.00 96.0558 72.6735 124.9079 229.5196 24 10.00 70.8795 32.6735 124.9079 229.5196 Table 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Comparison of result for five unit system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Method Minimum cost ($/24 h) SA 47,356 APSO 44,678 DE 43,213 HS 44367.23 HHS 43154.8554 Convergence plot for five unit system Fig 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Convergence plot for five unit system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Case 2: ten unit system In this test case the 10 unit system with valve point loading effect is considered and the data can be obtained from Balamurugan and Subramanian (2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>The system transmission loss is neglected and the load demand is considered over 24 h time interval.</sentence>
    <sentence>The algorithm parameters considered are population = 100, no of iteration = 2000, c1 = 2.1, c2 = 2.1, HMCR = 0.95, PPAR = 0.9 − 0.4.</sentence>
    <sentence>The simulation is performed for 25 trials and the obtained best optimum power generation value of all 10 generators in the 24 h scheduling horizon is given in Table 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>The mean time for the computation of solution by proposed method is 12.233 min.</sentence>
    <sentence>The comparison of convergence rate for the proposed algorithm with classical harmony search technique is depicted in Fig 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>The comparison of results obtained by proposed method with other reported results in the literature such as SQP, Hybrid EP with SQP, EP (Attaviriyanupap et al., 2002), DGPSO (Victoire &amp; Jeyakumar, 2005a), PSO-SQP(c) (Victoire &amp; Jeyakumar, 2005c), MHEP-SQP (Victoire &amp; Jeyakumar, 2005b), DE (Balamurugan &amp; Subramanian, 2008), MDE (Yuan, Anjunsu et al.</sentence>
    <sentence>(2008)), IPSO (Yuan, Anjunsu et al., 2009), Shor’s r-algorithm, DE, Hybrid DE (Yuan, Wang et al., 2009) is given in Table 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Result of 24 h DED for 10 unit system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Load hours Pg1 Pg2 Pg3 Pg4 Pg5 Pg6 Pg7 Pg8 Pg9 Pg10 1 150.0013 135.00 194.0448 60.0159 122.8694 122.478 129.5905 47.00 20.00 55.00 2 226.625 135.0009 191.4093 60.0103 122.8711 122.4755 129.5906 47.0171 20.0001 55.00 3 303.2479 135.00 185.1859 60.0001 172.7338 150.2411 129.5906 47.0006 20.00 55.00 4 379.8728 215.00 204.1551 60.0573 172.7392 122.5789 129.5905 47.0013 20.0049 55.00 5 456.4968 222.2665 186.7881 60.0001 172.7649 130.088 129.5942 47.0014 20.0001 55.00 6 456.4962 302.2658 262.4514 60.0006 172.733 122.4605 129.5904 47.0021 20.00 55.00 7 379.8737 309.5328 305.9238 110.0004 222.6128 122.4488 129.6063 47.0015 20.00 55.00 8 456.4977 309.6265 305.134 120.4158 172.7338 159.9999 129.5922 47.00 20.00 55.00 9 456.497 389.6265 323.2045 120.4808 222.5999 159.9999 129.5913 47.0002 20.00 55.00 10 456.5004 459.9997 320.8552 170.4624 222.598 159.9867 129.5908 47.007 49.9997 55.00 11 456.4988 460.00 339.9997 220.462 227.4392 159.9999 129.5933 77.007 20.00 55.00 12 456.4971 459.9999 339.9264 241.2634 242.4338 159.9769 129.5904 85.3121 49.9999 55.00 13 456.514 396.8677 304.8602 241.2476 222.6073 160.00 129.5908 85.3122 20.0003 55.00 14 456.4961 396.7994 294.3699 191.248 172.7333 122.4507 129.5906 85.3119 20.0003 55.00 15 379.8695 396.7982 285.1592 178.9724 122.8509 122.4483 129.5896 85.3118 20.00 55.00 16 303.2491 316.7985 317.8357 130.2852 73.0113 122.9172 129.5905 85.3123 20.0002 55.00 17 226.6212 309.5324 288.5409 120.2255 122.7606 122.4225 129.5905 85.3066 20.00 55.00 18 303.2501 309.5456 309.4559 120.4283 172.7348 122.6794 129.5959 85.3099 20.0001 55.00 19 379.8723 389.5454 301.0903 120.4148 172.7261 122.4485 129.5905 85.3121 20.00 55.00 20 456.4984 459.9999 339.9691 170.4137 222.5996 132.6169 129.5904 85.3118 20.0003 55.00 21 456.4928 396.6819 315.4599 120.4147 222.5997 122.4499 129.5889 85.3122 20.0001 55.00 22 379.8707 316.683 275.9265 70.4416 172.7312 122.4449 129.5904 85.3116 20.00 55.00 23 303.2502 236.7978 196.672 60.0036 122.8666 122.505 129.5914 85.3133 20.0001 55.00 24 226.6253 222.2661 189.6481 60.0136 73.0125 122.5236 129.5909 85.3124 20.0076 55.00 Convergence plot for 10 unit system Fig 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Convergence plot for 10 unit system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>Comparison of result for 10 unit system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Method Minimum cost ($/24 h) Method Minimum cost ($/24 h) SQP 1,051,163 Hybrid EP with SQP 1,035,748 EP 1,048,638 DGPSO 1,028,835 PSO-SQP(C) 1,027,334 MHEP-SQP 1,028,924 DE 1,019,786 MDE 1,031,612 IPSO 1,023,807 Shor’s r-algorithm 1,038,976 DE 1,033,958 Hybrid DE 1,031,077 HS 1,046,725.908 HHS 1,019,091.108 4.3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Case 3: thirty unit system The 10 unit test system is tripled to obtain the 30 units test system having same cost characteristics with valve point loading effect.</sentence>
    <sentence>Here also transmission loss is neglected and the loading pattern is taken as the three times the value which is considered in case2 for all 24 h time period.</sentence>
    <sentence>The algorithm parameters considered are population = 100, no of iteration = 5000, c1 = 2.1, c2 = 2.1, HMCR = 0.95, PPAR = 0.9 − 0.4.</sentence>
    <sentence>The simulation is performed for 25 trials.</sentence>
    <sentence>The mean time for the computation of solution by proposed method is 27.65 min.</sentence>
    <sentence>The comparison of results obtained by proposed method with other reported results in the literature such as DGPSO (Victoire &amp; Jeyakumar, 2005a), EP, MHEP-SQP (Victoire &amp; Jeyakumar, 2005b) and IPSO (Yuan, Anjunsu et al., 2009) is given in Table 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>Comparison of result of for 30 unit system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Method Minimum cost ($/24 h) DGPSO 3,148,992 EP 3,164,531 MHEP–SQP 3,151,445 IPSO 3,090,570 HS 3,143,253.84 HHS 3,057,313.39</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Conclusions">
    <sentence>In this paper the hybrid swarm intelligence based harmony search algorithm successfully implemented to solve the dynamic economic dispatch problem with non smooth cost characteristics.</sentence>
    <sentence>The constraints of this optimization problem were handled by penalty function method.</sentence>
    <sentence>The pitch adjustment step in classical harmony search is modified with the knowledge of swarm intelligence instead of random perturbation of distance bandwidth.</sentence>
    <sentence>The velocity based movement of particle with cognitive and social behavior makes the algorithm to have better exploration and faster convergence.</sentence>
    <sentence>The number of trials was performed for all three test cases, which shows the effectiveness of HHS algorithm to obtain better significant solution in solving the highly non-convex DELD problem.</sentence>
  </section>
</article>
