<article>
  <title>A narrative-based reasoning with applications in decision support for social service organizations</title>
  <abstract>
    <sentence>Nowadays, there is an increasing demand for incorporating unstructured narratives in decision support for knowledge-intensive industries such as healthcare and social service organizations.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, most of the current research on decision support systems (DSS) mainly focused on dealing with structured data and are inadequate to dealing with unstructured narratives such as clients’ records and stories.</sentence>
    <sentence>This paper presents a narrative-based reasoning (NBR) algorithm which incorporates the technologies of knowledge-based system (KBS), computational linguistics, and artificial intelligence (AI) for automatic processing unstructured narratives and inferring useful knowledge for decision support.</sentence>
    <sentence>A NBR enabled DSS has been built and was evaluated through a series of experiments conducted in early intervention of mental health of a social service company in Hong Kong.</sentence>
    <sentence>The performance of NBR was measured based on recall and precision and encouraging results were obtained.</sentence>
    <sentence>High recall and precision are achieved in the reasoning of unstructured data, and high recall is achieved for the association analysis.</sentence>
    <sentence>The results show that it is possible for inferring recommendations for problem solving from unstructured narratives automatically.</sentence>
    <sentence>Based on the approach, it helps to support knowledge workers with reliable suggestions on decision making so as to increase the quality of their solutions.</sentence>
  </abstract>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Concept association</keyword>
    <keyword>Knowledge-based systems</keyword>
    <keyword>Narrative-based reasoning</keyword>
    <keyword>Natural language processing</keyword>
    <keyword>Decision support system</keyword>
    <keyword>Health care</keyword>
    <keyword>Social service organizations</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <section name="Introduction">
    <sentence>Mental health problems impact seriously to the society.</sentence>
    <sentence>There is an increasing psychological morbidity of people which is illustrated by an increase in the incidence of suicide and the risk of developing depression, increasing rate of drug abuse and substance abuse, and drug related offending (Wang, Cheung, Lee, &amp; Kwok, 2007b).</sentence>
    <sentence>However, mental health care service providers are facing growing challenge owing to the diverse environmental changes such as increasing competition, constraining budget, high complication of social problems (Ferns, 1995; Savage, 1987).</sentence>
    <sentence>The increasing trend of psychological morbidity certainly adds burden to the mental health care providers for offering timely and quality services so as to maintain the health of the community.</sentence>
    <sentence>Moreover, changes in social welfare policy, in particular the subvention system and quality assurance mechanisms have posted tremendous demands on the mental health care providers, both in terms of service quantities and qualities.</sentence>
    <sentence>There is lacking psychiatric psychosis professional such as doctors, nurse and social workers.</sentence>
    <sentence>In some public hospitals, the social worker and client ratio is 1–100 and the nurse and client ratio is 1–50.</sentence>
    <sentence>Traditional approaches in mental health care, which social workers’ learning of practice wisdom depends on face-to-face sharing, may not be always available now.</sentence>
    <sentence>Due to the board range of knowledge and experience in mental health care, some researchers (e.g.</sentence>
    <sentence>Carlson, 1999; Kolbo &amp; Wahington, 1999; Schoech, 1999) mentioned that the application of decision support system (DSS) mimics the processes of performing task at skill levels comparable to human experts.</sentence>
    <sentence>DSS is an infrastructure and enabling technology for enhancing decision making process (Antony &amp; Santhanam, 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>The core components of DSS are knowledge base and reasoning mechanisms (Huang, 2009).</sentence>
    <sentence>The experience of knowledge workers is assimilated and stored in the knowledge base or knowledge repository in a certain format or schema.</sentence>
    <sentence>Moreover, the repository stores the knowledge invoked in prior decisions and retains the rules, policies and standard procedures of an organization (Hine &amp; Goul, 1998).</sentence>
    <sentence>The inference or reasoning mechanisms makes use the knowledge stored to deduce suggestions to a given problem (Chau &amp; Albermani, 2002).</sentence>
    <sentence>Based on DSS, the valuable knowledge that resides within individuals is thus identified and disseminated throughout the organization (Tan &amp; Platts, 2004).</sentence>
    <sentence>A number of DSSs have been built and applied to various areas which include performance assessment (Ammar, Duncombe, Jump, &amp; Wright, 2004; Wang, 2005; Wang, Huang, &amp; Lai, 2007), commercial loan underwriting (Kumra, Stein, &amp; Assersohn, 2006), logistics strategy design (Chow, Choy, Lee, &amp; Chan, 2005), farm productivity (Pomar &amp; Pomar, 2005), mergers and acquisitions (Wen, Wang, &amp; Wang, 2005a, 2005b), defense budget planning (Wen et al., 2005a, 2005b), earthquake design (Berrais, 2005), system dynamics (Yim, Kim, Kim, &amp; Kwahk, 2004), conveyor equipment selection (Fonseca, Uppal, &amp; Greene, 2004), customer service management (Cheung, Lee, Wang, Chu, &amp; To, 2003), etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, most of them are dealing with structured information.</sentence>
    <sentence>The use of unstructured narratives for decision support has received relatively little attention.</sentence>
    <sentence>In knowledge-intensive organizations such as healthcare and social service organizations, most of the knowledge resided in the unstructured narratives such as clients’ records and stories.</sentence>
    <sentence>For example, it is important in mental health care industry that most of the cases in mental health care are retained in terms of narratives.</sentence>
    <sentence>Narratives provide information how people deal successfully or unsuccessfully with real life problems.</sentence>
    <sentence>People can have a more comprehensible understanding on their difficulties and challenges by listening to the other’s similar stories since they are easy to remember, easy to understand and deal with human-like experiences (Gabriel, 2000).</sentence>
    <sentence>These stories also help people to adapt to the experience and discover new innovative ideas from others in order to solve their own problems (Lämsä &amp; Sintonen, 2006).</sentence>
    <sentence>In this paper, a narrative-based reasoning (NBR) algorithm is proposed with applications in decision support in mental health care.</sentence>
    <sentence>The proposed method aims at automatically processing the unstructured narrative information and suggesting recommendations for problem solving.</sentence>
    <sentence>It integrates the technologies of knowledge-based system (KBS), natural language processing (NLP) and artificial intelligence (AI).</sentence>
    <sentence>The NBR algorithm does not only help the knowledge workers to search relevant information easier by the enhanced indexing capability but also provides useful and reliable recommendations for the workers in problem solving so as to increase the quality of their solutions.</sentence>
    <sentence>A series of experiments have been carried out for measuring the performance of the purposed method based on real cases conducted in a Hong Kong based social service organization.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Related work">
    <sentence>A number of DSSs have been developed in the social services and health care industry.</sentence>
    <sentence>Special focus has been put on the rule-based systems, in which knowledge is retained in the knowledge base in the form of “if-then” rules.</sentence>
    <sentence>Upon rules definition, human decision making capability can be assimilated by the system and the social workers are assisted in the decision making process.</sentence>
    <sentence>For instance, Lifenet is a rule-based tool for the risk assessment of adolescent suicide (Ferns, 1995).</sentence>
    <sentence>It combines aspects of expert system and decision support technology.</sentence>
    <sentence>Its main functions are to provide paraprofessional caseworkers support in reaching unbiased and consistent risk assessments, and to recommend a course of action on the part of the caseworker.</sentence>
    <sentence>DISXPERT is a rule-based vocational rehabilitation risk assessment system (Nolan, 1997).</sentence>
    <sentence>It is similar to Lifenet but it has been applied to different aspects.</sentence>
    <sentence>There are also some DSSs developed for assisting social service based on case-based reasoning (CBR).</sentence>
    <sentence>CBR is a problem-solving approach that relies on past and similar cases to find solutions to new problems (Kolodner, 1993).</sentence>
    <sentence>It simulates human decision making processes and enables the reuse of previous experience.</sentence>
    <sentence>BOLERO is a case-based learning system for medical diagnosis and has been tested in the domain of diagnosing pneumonia (López &amp; Plaza, 1997).</sentence>
    <sentence>It aims at improving the performance of a rule-based diagnosis system by adapting its behavior using the most recent information available from the patients.</sentence>
    <sentence>Zhang, Lee, and Wong (1999) have proposed a knowledge-based approach, which combines CBR and RBR, for the design of intervention strategies for clinical incidents.</sentence>
    <sentence>Carlson (1999) made use of case-based reasoning to develop computerized guidance for effective practice.</sentence>
    <sentence>Frize and Walker (2000) have developed an intelligent decision support system (IDSS) for intensive care units using CBR.</sentence>
    <sentence>The system helps medical and nursing personnel to assess patient status, assists in making a diagnosis, and facilitates the selection of a course of therapy.</sentence>
    <sentence>Jain and Marling (2001) have built a case-based tool for treatment of Alzheimer’s disease.</sentence>
    <sentence>It proposed a new retrieval process that speeds up the retrieval process by not comparing with all cases in the case library.</sentence>
    <sentence>Alexandrini, Krechel, Maximini, and Wangenheim (2003) have proposed a CBR-based component that is capable of retrieval of the medical documents in written text format and to convert them into a structured report.</sentence>
    <sentence>Chang, Cheng, and Su (2004) have applied CBR to establish a continuous care information system of discharge planning.</sentence>
    <sentence>Hsu and Ho (2004) have developed a hybrid CBR system which combines CBR and some other artificial intelligence (AI) techniques for medical diagnosis.</sentence>
    <sentence>Its basic mechanism is CBR.</sentence>
    <sentence>The other AI techniques perform approximate matching to tolerate potential noise in case retrieval and used in case selection, adaptation and learning, which helps in selecting valuable features for the target case from existent ones as well as in pruning unnecessary search space.</sentence>
    <sentence>Trivedi, Kern, Grannemann, Altshuler, and Sunderajan (2004) have developed CompTMAP for implementing depression guidelines based on RBR.</sentence>
    <sentence>It provides a large range of support which includes diagnosis, treatment, follow-up, and preventive care and it can be incorporated into the clinical setting.</sentence>
    <sentence>Chang (2005) has applied CBR for the diagnostic screening of children with developmental delay.</sentence>
    <sentence>Wang, Cheung, et al.</sentence>
    <sentence>(2007b) developed a Knowledge-based Treatment Planning System (KBTPS) for providing recommendation of treatment planning of adolescent early intervention by combining CBR and several AI techniques.</sentence>
    <sentence>Although numerous DSSs have been built for supporting social services and health care, most of them are dealing with structured knowledge.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, DSS that makes use of the unstructured narrative knowledge for decision support has received relatively little attention.</sentence>
    <sentence>Narrative database is a technology for managing narrative knowledge.</sentence>
    <sentence>It aims at retention, reuse and analysis of the narrative knowledge within an organization.</sentence>
    <sentence>It not only allows people to capture a large amount of narratives at low cost, but also allows people to index those records to give existing and new staff access to “the wisdom of the elders” for decision support (Snowden, 2002).</sentence>
    <sentence>It provides a landscape of the narrative material based on the indexes.</sentence>
    <sentence>Narrative databases allow abstract searches by archetypes, themes, intention, emotional level and perspective in such a way that multiple stories are encountered from which the listener can synthesize their own interpretations.</sentence>
    <sentence>Narrative databases also create a supporting “worse cases system” in which the stories of failures are more likely to foster success in the future (Snowden, 2000).</sentence>
    <sentence>However, narrative databases are always tagged or indexed by human, which is expensive and time consuming.</sentence>
    <sentence>It also offers limited decision support for problem solving.</sentence>
    <sentence>It provides similar stories to the knowledge workers without any recommendations or suggestions.</sentence>
    <sentence>It relies on workers to make sense to the previous stories.</sentence>
    <sentence>As a result, the NBR algorithm proposed in this paper attempts to address the limitations of narrative databases and traditional DSS.</sentence>
    <sentence>It provides an important means for automatically indexing and analyzing the unstructured narrative information and makes use of them to infer useful recommendations for supporting decision making for problem solving.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Narrative-based reasoning (NBR)">
    <sentence>In mental health care, the information of a client is always retained in cases.</sentence>
    <sentence>Each case consists of a problem or situation of a client and some solutions in terms of planning or actions to the problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>The problem of the cases can be divided into structured parts and unstructured parts.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 1 depicts the structured and unstructured parts of a mental health care assessment case.</sentence>
    <sentence>The structured parts consist of quantitative parameters, or optional items which have a range of well defined choices from which the worker may make a selection.</sentence>
    <sentence>The unstructured parts consist of narratives or texts.</sentence>
    <sentence>Traditionally, the structured parts of a case are analyzed by case-based reasoning (CBR) while the unstructured parts have been analyzed manually.</sentence>
    <sentence>In this paper, the unstructured parts are analyzed by the narrative-based reasoning (NBR).</sentence>
    <sentence>An example of the structured and unstructured parts of a case Fig 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>An example of the structured and unstructured parts of a case.</sentence>
    <sentence>The difference of the processes flows of CBR and NBR is shown in Fig 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>After the user enters the problem situation, the problem can be divided into structured parts and unstructured parts.</sentence>
    <sentence>CBR can be used to carry out similarity analysis to compare the similarities among the structured parts of inputted problem and the cases that have been stored previously.</sentence>
    <sentence>The most similar case is then retrieved and its solution is used as recommendation for the problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>The recommendation is reviewed, revised, and retained in the knowledge repository (KR) for future reuse.</sentence>
    <sentence>For proposed the NBR, it consists of three major components which are Key Concept Extraction Module, Similarity Analysis Module and Association Analysis Module, respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>The unstructured parts of the problem are processed by the Key Concept Extraction Module which extracts and consolidates the key concepts of the problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>Recommendations are generated based on both Similarity Analysis Module and Association Analysis Module.</sentence>
    <sentence>The most similar case is retrieved based on the extracted concepts of the problem and that of previous cases.</sentence>
    <sentence>The concepts of the retrieved case’s solution are used as recommendation for the inputted problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>For the Association Analysis Module, it associates the key concepts of the problem with that of the previous cases.</sentence>
    <sentence>The associated concepts among the solutions of the previous cases are extracted as recommendation for solving the problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>Similar to CBR, the recommendation is then revised and retained in the KR for future reuse.</sentence>
    <sentence>Process flows of narrative-based reasoning (NBR) and case-based reasoning (CBR) Fig 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Process flows of narrative-based reasoning (NBR) and case-based reasoning (CBR).</sentence>
    <sentence>Key concept extraction In order to analyze the unstructured parts of problem, it requires the extraction of the key concepts resided in the texts.</sentence>
    <sentence>Single word is often too general in represent the meanings or ambiguous to represent a concept.</sentence>
    <sentence>Multi-word phrases can be more specific and desirable.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, multi-word phrases have no lexical boundaries in texts, which makes them difficult to be identified (Tseng, Lin, &amp; Lin, 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>In this paper, a key concept extraction algorithm is developed for extracting multi-word phrases while any corpora, lexicons, or dictionaries are not required.</sentence>
    <sentence>It makes use of the syntactic structure of the text to find the relations between the words.</sentence>
    <sentence>The key concepts can be extracted from the text itself rather than retrieved from predefined lexicons.</sentence>
    <sentence>Hence, it can be used in any knowledge domains without the need for initial knowledge acquisition.</sentence>
    <sentence>Generally, the subject of a sentence represents a concept.</sentence>
    <sentence>The object of a sentence, which is in the verbal phrase, represents a second concept.</sentence>
    <sentence>The algorithm extracts all the noun phrases inside the text and consolidates them into a list of key concepts.</sentence>
    <sentence>As shown in Figs.</sentence>
    <sentence>3 and 4, the unstructured text is first divided into tokens by regular expressions such as the new line character, full stop, question mark, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>The tokens are then tagged with its parts-of-speech (POS) using a POS tagger developed by Schmid (1994).</sentence>
    <sentence>Each token is merged with its nearby token as noun phrases based on their POS.</sentence>
    <sentence>If their POS are nouns, adjectives, gerunds, or preposition “of”, then they are merged.</sentence>
    <sentence>Simple rules are used to deal with spelling variants and syntactic variants as shown in Table 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Moreover, it is interesting to note that a longer word string is usually a preferred concept (Tseng et al., 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>To obtain a longer word string, the extracted noun phrases are filtered based on the following heuristic rules as follows: • Rule 1: Given two phrases t1 and t2, if t2 matches t1 and t1 is additionally modified by certain terms or adjectives, then t2 is removed.</sentence>
    <sentence>For example, t1 = “credit card”, t2 = “card”, t2 is removed.</sentence>
    <sentence>• Rule 2: Given two phrases t1 and t2, if t2’s alphabet letters matches the first letters of words of t1, then t2 is considered as the abbreviation of t1 and t2 is removed.</sentence>
    <sentence>For example, t1 = “natural language processing”, t2 = “NLP”, t2 is removed.</sentence>
    <sentence>Process flows of the key concept extraction algorithm Fig 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Process flows of the key concept extraction algorithm.</sentence>
    <sentence>The key concept extraction algorithm Fig 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>The key concept extraction algorithm.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Examples of the variation types.</sentence>
    <sentence>Variation type Example Number “techniques” and “technique” Spelling “cluster-based” and “cluster based” Syntactic “information retrieval” and “retrieval of information” After the key concept extraction, the unstructured text is indexed with its key concepts.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is then used in the similarity analysis and association analysis for generating recommendations.</sentence>
    <sentence>Similarity analysis Some decision makers believe that the current problem can be solved by studying similar cases that were successfully resolved in the past.</sentence>
    <sentence>Similarity analysis is developed based on this idea.</sentence>
    <sentence>It searches for similar cases by quantifying the cases in order to calculate the similarity among cases.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the present study, the similarity between the new problem and the old cases is determined by the nearest neighbor matching (Aamodt &amp; Plaza, 1994) as shown by Eq (1) (1) where m is the number of fields, wj is the weighting of the jth field, and are value of the jth field of the input problem and that of the old cases, is the similarity function for the jth field.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the present study, the similarity between the fields of unstructured texts is determined by the similarity between the key concepts of the unstructured texts.</sentence>
    <sentence>The similarity is calculated by Eq (2) (2) where vi and vr are key concept lists of the jth field of the input problem and that of the retrieved case, respectively; vijn is the key concept n in the concept list vij; |vij ∩ vrj| is the number of concepts jointly appearing in vij and vrj; |vij ∩ vrj| is the number of unique concepts in vij and vrj, concepts are considered as similar if they are identical, or they satisfy the condition in Rule 1 or Rule 2 that mentioned Section 3.1.</sentence>
    <sentence>After determining the similarities of the old cases in the repository, the case with the highest similarity is retrieved as the recommendation for the inputted problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>Association analysis Contrast to similarity analysis, cognitive psychology stated that people do not learn by memorizing, instead, they learn by summarizing, relating, and organizing concepts into their cognitive structures (Ausubel, 1963).</sentence>
    <sentence>New knowledge is assimilated into their cognitive structures through construction and not merely acquired (Novak, 1990).</sentence>
    <sentence>It has been proven that the cognitive structures can be constructed by the association analysis of transactional cases in terms of maps or networks, and it sometime performs better than that for the similarity analysis (Wang, Cheung, Lee, &amp; Kwok, 2008).</sentence>
    <sentence>Wang et al.</sentence>
    <sentence>(2008) have proposed a concept association algorithm dealing with structured information.</sentence>
    <sentence>Based on the previous work from Wang et al.</sentence>
    <sentence>(2008), a concept association algorithm is proposed to suit the nature of unstructured information for the NBR.</sentence>
    <sentence>A schematic diagram of the concept association algorithm is shown in Fig 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>The cognitive structure is an association network which consists of problem concepts, solution concepts, and the association links among the problem and solution concepts.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 6 shows the learning phase of the concept association algorithm, which constructs the association network from a list of transactional cases.</sentence>
    <sentence>The unstructured parts of the problems of the cases are first indexed by the Key Concept Extraction Module.</sentence>
    <sentence>The extracted concepts are used to represent the problem concepts.</sentence>
    <sentence>Similarly, the unstructured parts of the solutions of the cases are also indexed to form a list of solution concepts.</sentence>
    <sentence>The association between a problem concept and a solution concept is determined by the conditional probability as shown in Eq (3) (3) where Cp is the problem concept and Cs is the solution concept.</sentence>
    <sentence>A schematic diagram of the concept association algorithm Fig 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>A schematic diagram of the concept association algorithm.</sentence>
    <sentence>The learning phase of the concept association algorithm Fig 6.</sentence>
    <sentence>The learning phase of the concept association algorithm.</sentence>
    <sentence>The application phase of the concept association algorithm is shown in Fig 7.</sentence>
    <sentence>When there is a new problem, the key concepts of the problem are extracted to form a list of problem concepts.</sentence>
    <sentence>Based on the trained concept network, the activation level of a solution concept is determined by the maximum value of the association level of the problem concepts associated with that particular associated solution concept, which is shown in Eq (4) (4) where Cpj is the jth problem concept of the inputted problem.</sentence>
    <sentence>The application phase of the concept association algorithm Fig 7.</sentence>
    <sentence>The application phase of the concept association algorithm.</sentence>
    <sentence>The solution concepts which have a higher activation level than a predefined threshold are retrieved as the recommendation.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Experiments and results">
    <sentence>To verify the performance of the NBR algorithm, a series of experiments have been conducted in a social service organization in Hong Kong.</sentence>
    <sentence>The experiment setup for measuring the performance of NBR is shown in Fig 8.</sentence>
    <sentence>Real case data are collected from a department of the social service organization.</sentence>
    <sentence>The selected department is responsible for providing services on early intervention of mental healthcare to the adolescents.</sentence>
    <sentence>There is a lot of information needed to be recorded for every single case.</sentence>
    <sentence>It includes the personal data, mental health assessment, development history, suicidal history, family background, treatment records, review records, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>The data of the assessment form of early intervention of mental health is used in this experiment, which consists of both structured and unstructured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>Ninety-five past cases handled during the period from October 2004 to September 2008 are used in this experiment.</sentence>
    <sentence>The experiment setup for measuring the performance of NBR Fig 8.</sentence>
    <sentence>The experiment setup for measuring the performance of NBR.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 2 shows the data fields of the assessment form.</sentence>
    <sentence>“Case ID” and “Date of Assessment” are the indexes of the cases.</sentence>
    <sentence>“Father Relation”, “Mother Relation”, “Sibling Relation”, “Peer Relation”, “Academic Performance”, “Motivation”, and “Insight” are the structured data fields that contain standard options for the social workers to choose so as to describe the situation of their clients.</sentence>
    <sentence>“Psychosocial History” and “Impression” are the unstructured data fields that contain natural language text entered by the social workers so as to describe the situation of their clients.</sentence>
    <sentence>“Intervention Plan” and “Treatment Plan” are the unstructured data fields which are inputted by social workers who describe their planning actions for helping the client.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the experiment, the data of the structured data fields are considered as the structured problem data.</sentence>
    <sentence>The data of the unstructured data fields are processed by the Key Concept Extraction Module.</sentence>
    <sentence>“Psychosocial History” and “Impression” are considered as the unstructured problem data.</sentence>
    <sentence>“Intervention Plan” and “Treatment Plan” are considered as the solution data.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Assessment form of early intervention of mental health.</sentence>
    <sentence>Field Data value Problem/solution Case ID Number Index Date of Assessment Date Index Father Relation Choices among good, fair, poor, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>Structured problem data Mother Relation Choices among good, fair, poor, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>Structured problem data Sibling Relation Choices among good, fair, poor, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>Structured problem data Peer Relation Choices among good, fair, poor, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>Structured problem data Academic Performance Choices among good, fair, poor, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>Structured problem data Psychosocial History Unstructured text Unstructured problem data Motivation Choices among high, fair, low, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>Structured problem data Insight Choices among good, fair, poor, etc.</sentence>
    <sentence>Structured problem data Impression Unstructured text Unstructured problem data Intervention Plan Unstructured text Solution data Treatment Plan Unstructured text Solution data The performance of similarity analysis of structured data is measured based on the experiment flow as shown in Fig 9.</sentence>
    <sentence>Cases are extracted from the testing cases which are sorted by the “Date of Assessment”.</sentence>
    <sentence>For each case, it is extracted into the structured data fields and the solution fields.</sentence>
    <sentence>The structured data fields of the extracted case are compared with the learned cases by similarity analysis.</sentence>
    <sentence>The suggested solution by the similarity analysis and the extracted solution fields are processed by the key concept extraction.</sentence>
    <sentence>The extracted key concepts from the suggested solution and the solution fields are compared based on recall and precision analysis.</sentence>
    <sentence>The recall and precision are defined as Eqs.</sentence>
    <sentence>(5) and (6), respectively (5) (6) where Cp and Cp are key concept lists of the suggested solution and the actual solution, respectively; |Cs| is the number of concepts in Cp.</sentence>
    <sentence>|Cs ∩ Cp| is the number of concepts jointly appearing in |Cs| and |Cp|.</sentence>
    <sentence>Concepts are considered as similar if they are identical, or they satisfy the condition of Rule 1 or Rule 2 as mentioned in Section 3.1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Experimental flow of similarity analysis of structured data Fig 9.</sentence>
    <sentence>Experimental flow of similarity analysis of structured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>After the analysis of the recall and precision, the case is retained to the learning cases for enhancing the reasoning capability.</sentence>
    <sentence>Another testing case is extracted for evaluation until all cases have been measured.</sentence>
    <sentence>For the measurement of the performance of similarity analysis and association analysis of unstructured data, they are carried out based on the experiment flow as shown in Fig 10.</sentence>
    <sentence>The same data set is used for measuring the structured and unstructured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>For each of the testing cases, it is extracted into the unstructured data fields and the solution fields.</sentence>
    <sentence>The key concepts are extracted from the unstructured data fields and they are used for similarity analysis and association analysis.</sentence>
    <sentence>Similar to the experiment of similarity analysis of structured data, the suggested solution by the similarity analysis and the extracted solution fields are processed by the key concept extraction.</sentence>
    <sentence>The extracted key concepts from the suggested solution and the solution fields are compared by recall and precision analysis.</sentence>
    <sentence>Since the suggested solution of association analysis is a list of concepts, it is directly compared with the key concepts of the actual solution based on the recall and precision analysis.</sentence>
    <sentence>After the recall and precision analysis, the case is retained as the learning cases and association network.</sentence>
    <sentence>The evaluations continue until all cases have been measured.</sentence>
    <sentence>Experiment flow of similarity analysis and association analysis of unstructured… Fig 10.</sentence>
    <sentence>Experiment flow of similarity analysis and association analysis of unstructured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 3 shows the averaged recall and precision of the different analyses.</sentence>
    <sentence>As shown in Fig 11, the recall and precision increase steadily with the increasing number of cases in the similarity analysis of structured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>The averaged recall and precision are 0.1130 and 0.1029, respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 12 shows the recall and precision of the similarity analysis of unstructured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>Based on the results, the recall and precision increase more rapidly with the increasing number of cases and the averaged recall and precision are doubled which are 0.2315 and 0.2252, respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>It shows that it is more accurate in using unstructured data instead of structured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>A threshold is needed to be set for the association analysis.</sentence>
    <sentence>Fig 13 shows the averaged recall and precision of association analysis of unstructured data with threshold ranged from 0 to 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Since a higher threshold means that more concepts are filtered and thus fewer concepts are remained as the suggested solution, the recall is decreasing and the precision is increasing with the increasing threshold.</sentence>
    <sentence>Comparing with the similarity analysis, the association analysis is able to achieve a higher recall but a lower precision.</sentence>
    <sentence>For instance, when the threshold is equal to 0.4, the averaged recall of association analysis is higher than that of similarity analysis by 0.3581 − 0.2315 = 0.1266, while the precision of association analysis is lower than that of similarity analysis by 0.2252 − 0.0534 = 0.1718.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Averaged recall and precision of the analyses.</sentence>
    <sentence>Analysis Avg.</sentence>
    <sentence>recall Avg.</sentence>
    <sentence>precision Similarity analysis of structured data 0.1130 0.1029 Similarity analysis of unstructured data 0.2315 0.2252 Association analysis of unstructured data (threshold = 0.4) 0.3581 0.0534 Recall and precision of similarity analysis of structured data Fig 11.</sentence>
    <sentence>Recall and precision of similarity analysis of structured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>Recall and precision of similarity analysis of unstructured data Fig 12.</sentence>
    <sentence>Recall and precision of similarity analysis of unstructured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>Recall and precision of association analysis of unstructured data Fig 13.</sentence>
    <sentence>Recall and precision of association analysis of unstructured data.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Conclusion">
    <sentence>Decisions must be made in dynamic and increasingly rapidly changing environment.</sentence>
    <sentence>Traditional decision support systems (DSS) in health care industry focus on the analysis of structured data and information, which are inadequate for retrieving important information and providing reliable recommendations.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is interesting to note that sharing experience and lesson learnt for decision making through stories or narrative is emerging to exchange and consolidate knowledge.</sentence>
    <sentence>Narratives have several advantages which provoke openness to multiple perspectives.</sentence>
    <sentence>They aid in coping with complexity.</sentence>
    <sentence>Moreover, they give meaning to events.</sentence>
    <sentence>There is a need for the development of a DSS which embraces the analysis of unstructured narrative information so as to search the lesson learnt from previous narratives and to provide constructive and reliable recommendations.</sentence>
    <sentence>In this paper, a narrative-based reasoning (NBR) algorithm is proposed for achieving the above purposes.</sentence>
    <sentence>The NBR consists of a Key Concept Extraction Module, a Similarity Analysis Module and an Association Analysis Module.</sentence>
    <sentence>The proposed NBR communicates a vast amount of information in terms of narratives or stories and automatically indexes the narratives with their key concepts, which helps to search the relevant information for problem-solving and further analyses.</sentence>
    <sentence>A similarity analysis and an association analysis are used to deduce the solutions of the problem based on the inference among the previous narratives.</sentence>
    <sentence>A NBR enabled DSS has been built for the case management of the mental health service in social service organization which is knowledge-intensive industry.</sentence>
    <sentence>A series of experiments have been carried out in a social service company in Hong Kong so as to compare the performance of the inference engines with structured and unstructured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>The results show that the recall and precision of using unstructured data increase more rapidly with the increasing number of cases than that of using structured data.</sentence>
    <sentence>The averaged recall and precision are significantly improved (i.e.</sentence>
    <sentence>improved from 0.1130 to 0.2315 and from 0.1029 to 0.2252, respectively).</sentence>
    <sentence>By comparing the similarity analysis and association analysis, the association analysis is able to achieve a higher recall but a lower precision.</sentence>
    <sentence>Further work will be done on measuring the similarity among the key concepts so as to a more precise determination on the similarity analysis and association analysis.</sentence>
    <sentence>In addition to the social service and health industry, potential applications of the tool can also be found in other industries.</sentence>
  </section>
</article>
