<article>
  <title>An optimal tumor marker group-coupled artificial neural network for diagnosis of lung cancer</title>
  <abstract>
    <sentence>Background Epidemiological statistics has shown that there are approximately 1.2 million new cases of lung cancer diagnosed every year and the death rate of these patients is 17.8%.</sentence>
    <sentence>Earlier diagnosis is key to promote the five-year survival rate of these cancer patients.</sentence>
    <sentence>Some tumor markers have been found to be valuable for earlier diagnosis, but a single marker has limitation in its sensitivity and specificity of cancer diagnosis.</sentence>
    <sentence>To improve the efficiency of diagnosis, several distinct tumor marker groups are combined together using a mathematical evaluation model, called artificial neural network (ANN).</sentence>
    <sentence>Lung cancer markers have been identified to include carcinoembryonic antigen, carcinoma antigen 125, neuron specific enolase, β2-microglobulin, gastrin, soluble interleukin-6 receptor, sialic acid, pseudouridine, nitric oxide, and some metal ions.</sentence>
    <sentence>Methods These tumor markers were measured through distinct experimental procedures in 50 patients with lung cancer, 40 patients with benign lung diseases, and 50 cases for a normal control group.</sentence>
    <sentence>The most valuable were selected into an optimal tumor marker group by multiple logistic regression analysis.</sentence>
    <sentence>The optimal marker group-coupled ANN model was employed as an intelligent diagnosis system.</sentence>
    <sentence>Results We have presented evidence that this system is superior to a traditional statistical method, its diagnosis specificity significantly improved from 72.0% to 100.0% and its accuracy increased from 71.4% to 92.8%.</sentence>
    <sentence>Conclusions The ANN-based system may provide a rapid and accurate diagnosis tool for lung cancer.</sentence>
  </abstract>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Artificial neural network</keyword>
    <keyword>Diagnosis</keyword>
    <keyword>Lung cancer</keyword>
    <keyword>Tumor marker</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <section name="Introduction">
    <sentence>Lung cancer is one of the most commonly occurring malignant tumors in the world, and especially in the China (Chinese report of Smoking and Health, 2006).</sentence>
    <sentence>Epidemiology has revealed that there are approximately 1.2 million new cases of lung cancer diagnosed every year and the death rate of these malignant patients is 17.8% (Strauss, Dominioni, &amp; Jett, 2005).</sentence>
    <sentence>In fact, the rate of correct diagnosis is relatively low because during the early stage of lung cancer the patients do not have specific symptoms that are recognized by physicians.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, some tumor biomarkers become present in the blood, urine or tissue of these pre-clinical cancer patients.</sentence>
    <sentence>Thus, there is sufficient evidence for the use of tumor markers for the diagnosis of cancer, staging, monitoring of treatment response and follow-up in specific patient populations (Li, 2000).</sentence>
    <sentence>Accumulating evidence has suggested more than one hundred tumor markers (Wang, Zhang, Cui, &amp; Jiang, 2005).</sentence>
    <sentence>For example, carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) is a glycoprotein produced by a number of tissues with malignant tumours and benign diseases and it is measured to become present and increases in the circulating blood of cancer patients (Sugarbaker, 1985).</sentence>
    <sentence>Carcinoma antigen 125 (CA125) was initially identified as an ovarian cancer-associated antigen, but it was later detected in non-small cell lung cancer (Diez et al., 1995).</sentence>
    <sentence>It has, however, been shown that CA125 possesses low diagnosis sensitivity, ranging from 34% to 62% (Diez et al., 1994).</sentence>
    <sentence>Progastrin-releasing peptide and neuron specific enolase (NSE) were suggested as two biomarkers for the malignancy of small cell lung cancer (Cho, 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>A significantly high concentration of pseudouridine, a degradative product of transfer ribonucleic acid, was found in the urine of patients with lung cancers, when compared to either those patients with pulmonary infectious diseases or healthy controls (Tamura, Fujii, Nakano, Hada, &amp; Higashino, 1986).</sentence>
    <sentence>Sialic acid in blood may be regarded as a useful marker for a variety of cancers, but its diagnosis specificity is relatively low (Paszkowska, Berbeć, &amp; Cybulski, 1997).</sentence>
    <sentence>Although the role of the soluble form of interleukin-6 receptor (sIL-6R) is unclear, an increase in the amount of this receptor was observed in various malignant diseases, including lung cancer (Hoheisel et al., 1998).</sentence>
    <sentence>In addition, it has been shown that an increase in serum levels of copper (Cu) and zinc (Zn) ions, and their concentration ratio ([Cu2+]/[Zn2+]) are positively correlated with the malignant degree of lung cancer (Ferrigno, Buccheri, &amp; Camilla, 1999).</sentence>
    <sentence>Most of these tumor markers are however inefficient in diagnosing lung cancers.</sentence>
    <sentence>No tumor marker is ideal by the strict definition that it is easily and reproducibly measured only in cancer patients and also that its value correlates with either the pathology stages or the patient response to clinical treatment (Healthcar, 2005).</sentence>
    <sentence>This is based on the fact that a single marker has limitation in sensitivity and specificity and does not satisfy the requirement for fast and correct diagnosis.</sentence>
    <sentence>To improve the correct rate of diagnosis for lung cancer, some valuable tumor markers were optimally selected and grouped through multiple logistic regressions (MLR).</sentence>
    <sentence>The latter is a commonly accepted statistical approach to assess association between an antecedent characteristic (i.e., risk factor) and a quantal outcome (i.e., probability of disease occurrence), and to adjust for potential confounding effects of other covariates (Li, Gao, &amp; Qian, 1996; Lee, 1986).</sentence>
    <sentence>The MLR thus provides a statistical model to test whether such marker factors associate with cancer diagnosis (Fan et al., 2006).</sentence>
    <sentence>The most valuable of 12 tumor markers were selected into an optimal group by using the MLR.</sentence>
    <sentence>The correlation of each of these markers with the malignant disease was also established in this study.</sentence>
    <sentence>Interestingly, it is clear that a mathematical model, called artificial neural network (ANN), is constructed on the basis of a biological neural network system (An, 2001).</sentence>
    <sentence>We have combined both the ANN and MLR to develop an intelligent diagnosis system, called the optimal tumor marker group-coupled ANN, so as to improve the sensitivity, specificity and accuracy of diagnosis for lung cancer.</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Materials and methods">
    <sentence>Collection of samples Fifty cases of lung cancer were collected from the First Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University between 2004 and 2005.</sentence>
    <sentence>All these cases were confirmed by pathohistological diagnosis.</sentence>
    <sentence>Twenty of these fifty cases were small cell lung cancer, and the remaining 30 cases were non small cell lung cancer including 12 cases of squamous cell cancers and 18 cases of adenocarcinoma.</sentence>
    <sentence>They were also classified according to the histological criteria recommended by the World Health Organization; the number of cases that were identified for the TNM stage II, III and IV are 16, 16 and 18, respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>Blood samples were taken from these patients after fasting overnight.</sentence>
    <sentence>Subsequently, the sera were separated and stored at −40 °C until test.</sentence>
    <sentence>Similarly, urine samples were also collected and stored at −80 °C.</sentence>
    <sentence>In addition, samples were collected from 40 cases with benign lung diseases; they included 10 patients with pulmonary tuberculosis, 10 with chronic bronchitis, 10 with bronchoalveolitis, 7 with bronchiectasis and 3 with bronchial asthma.</sentence>
    <sentence>In addition, 50 samples from normal people were used as internal controls.</sentence>
    <sentence>The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee at the University of Zhengzhou, China.</sentence>
    <sentence>Measurements of tumor markers Amounts of β2-microglobulin (β2-MG), CEA and gastrin in serum samples were determined by radioimmunoassay (Wang et al., 2001).</sentence>
    <sentence>These assay kits were purchased from the Isotope Institute, Chinese Academy of Atom Energy Sciences (Beijing, China).</sentence>
    <sentence>Values of CA125 and NSE were determined by immunoradiometric assay kits provided by the Tumor Institute, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences (Beijing, China) Wang et al., 2001.</sentence>
    <sentence>Radioactivity of all five markers was measured in a well-type gamma counter FJ-2003/50 (Auto-Gamma; Xian 262 Electronic Factory, Xian, China) and expressed as counts per minute.</sentence>
    <sentence>The sIL-6R was determined by an enzyme-linked immuosorbent assay kit (from the French International Immunity Corporation, France) (Wu., Wu, Wang, Qu, &amp; Xiang, 2002).</sentence>
    <sentence>Three metal ions Cu2+, Zn2+ and Ca2+ were detected by an atomic absorption spectrophotometer (AA-6401F, Shimadzu).</sentence>
    <sentence>Parameters of the instrument for determining these metal ions were shown in Table 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>The determination was carried out after a volume of 0.4 ml serum was diluted with 6% n-butanol solution (Zhao, Han, &amp; Jing, 1998).</sentence>
    <sentence>The serum levels of Cu2+, Zn2+ and Ca2+ were calculated using the following regression equations: (1) (2) (3) Table 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Parameters of the instrument for determining the serum metal ions.</sentence>
    <sentence>Element Wavelength (nm) Lamp current (mA) Slit width (nm) Burner height (mm) Acetylene pressure (kg/cm) Zn 213.8 10.0 1.3 7.5 0.2 Cu 324.8 7.5 1.3 7.5 0.3 Ca 422.7 7.0 1.3 7.5 0.3 The air pressure was controlled at 1.60 kg cm-1 in all experiments.</sentence>
    <sentence>Urine samples were clarified by centrifugation at 3000 rpm for 10 min at 4 °C.</sentence>
    <sentence>The supernatants were saved and then filtered through a nitrocellulose membrane with a pore diameter of 0.22 μm.</sentence>
    <sentence>These flow-through samples were diluted in 1 ml of 0.02 mol/L phosphate salt buffer (pH 4.0).</sentence>
    <sentence>Ten microliters of clarified urine samples were analyzed by the Waters HPLC using a 250 × 4.6 mm column of Spherisorb ODS C18 (5 μm) in a mobile phase of 0.02 mol/L KH2PO4 (pH 4.0), and measured with a 996-photodiode-array detector at 254 nm (Wu, Zhou, Wu, Cao, &amp; Liu.</sentence>
    <sentence>2002).</sentence>
    <sentence>Subsequently, concentrations of pseudourine and trophicardyl in urines were computed according to the equations listed below: (4) (5) In addition, serum levels of nitric oxide and sialic acid were detected by a 722-type visible spectrophotometer (Shanghai Cany Precision Instruments Ltd, China) (Wu et al., 2001).</sentence>
    <sentence>Artificial neural network (ANN) model A neural network is an attempt to simulate the brain because biological neurons are extracted and applied to simulations.</sentence>
    <sentence>A theorized mathematic model called ANN is established on the basis of the brain neural network.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ANN can test trends and important features in relatively complex information.</sentence>
    <sentence>It can act as a pattern processor by two phases in information processing; they are the training phase and the test phase.</sentence>
    <sentence>In the former phase, a set of training data is used to determine the weight parameters that define the neural model.</sentence>
    <sentence>This trained neural model is used later in the test phase to process real test patterns and yield classification results (Andina, 2007; Bicciato, 2004).</sentence>
    <sentence>There are many types of artificial neural network, but all of them share the same basic structure (Fig 1).</sentence>
    <sentence>Three components of the structure include a set of input nodes, one or more layers of hidden nodes and an additional set of output nodes.</sentence>
    <sentence>The input nodes take in the information, which is supplied with activation values.</sentence>
    <sentence>The activation of the information from the input nodes is passed through the hidden layers to the output nodes.</sentence>
    <sentence>Thus, the output could, to a certain degree, reflect the input if a network is trained properly.</sentence>
    <sentence>Schematic representation of a typical ANN structure Fig 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Schematic representation of a typical ANN structure.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ANN consists of three layers of nodes; they are an input layer, a hidden layer and output layer, respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>For detailed description, see the text.</sentence>
    <sentence>In this study, the input data are the tumor marker values, ai.</sentence>
    <sentence>The input nodes are linear, Oi = ai, and serve to buffer the input data to the hidden nodes.</sentence>
    <sentence>Their linear outputs are passed to the nodes in the hidden nodes through weighted connections, as shown in Fig 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>The outputs of the hidden layer nodes are given by weighted sum, Oj = f(ΣOiWji), after transformed by some function, f(x).</sentence>
    <sentence>The weights connecting the bias nodes to the next layer of nodes are automatically adjusted during the training process to permit incorporation of non-zero intercepts into neural network diagnosis models.</sentence>
    <sentence>When the number of neurons in hidden layer was 3, the minimum standard error of prediction was obtained.</sentence>
    <sentence>Subsequently, we investigated whether the training speed influences the standard error of prediction.</sentence>
    <sentence>It was shown that there was a little difference between 0.5 and 2.0, but this difference could affect convergence speed.</sentence>
    <sentence>We selected 0.7 as a training speed.</sentence>
    <sentence>During the training process, samples of distinct prediction sets were standardized to adjust sigmoid function.</sentence>
    <sentence>The training process would be stopped when the desired level of precision was obtained in the estimated class.</sentence>
    <sentence>The artificial neural network software was provided by the Center of Computer Analysis of China Pharmaceutical University (Nanjing, China).</sentence>
    <sentence>Analyses for multiple logistic regression and statistics Its basic principle is similar to linear stepwise regression, which include stepwise, forward and backward.</sentence>
    <sentence>This method is extremely similar to the process of linear regression in screening variables, but the statistical value is not the F of the linear regression but usually selecting variable forward is used with the score test, and eliminating variable backward with the Wald test (Jiang, 1997; Lee, 1986).</sentence>
    <sentence>The MLR was analyzed with the LOGISTIC program described in the SAS 12.0 software and the related data were processed using a LEGEND computer with the Intel (R) Pentium (R) CPU 2.40-GHz and 256-MB.</sentence>
    <sentence>Most of the experimental data were in normal distribution after converted to logarithm, all of which accorded with normal distribution.</sentence>
    <sentence>The results are expressed as mean value ( ) ± standard deviation (S).</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Results">
    <sentence>The values of some tumor markers measured in lung cancer As shown in Table 2, the values of 12 indexes, including tumor markers CEA, β2-MG, gastrin, CA125, NSE, sIL-6R, pseudourine, nitric oxide, sialic acid and metal ions, were measured in lung cancer, benign pulmonary diseases and normal control groups.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>The values of 12 indexes measured in three distinct groups.</sentence>
    <sentence>Tumor marker Lung cancer (n = 50) Benign disease (n = 40) Normal control (n = 50) CEA (μg L-1) 31.58 ± 7.79 10.62 ± 7.27 9.60 ± 2.45 CA125 (mg L-1) 56.18 ± 46.20 31.71 ± 26.86 12.44 ± 6.44 Gastrin (ng L-1) 172.70 ± 68.19 61.66 ± 22.96 60.74 ± 19.72 NSE (μg L-1) 41.03 ± 21.30 7.32 ± 3.33 6.96 ± 3.24 β2-MG (mg L-1) 2.17 ± 0.92 1.77 ± 0.50 1.53 ± 0.34 Sialic acid (mg L-1) 1082.00 ± 128.31 925.27 ± 117.37 795.00 ± 122.81 sIL-6R (μg L-1) 95.99 ± 26.56 93.47 ± 19.07 78.34 ± 19.10 NO (μmol L-1) 48.58 ± 33.98 70.83 ± 44.51 84.78 ± 33.66 Psedouridin/Inosine 25.92 ± 7.23 24.84 ± 6.20 23.15 ± 3.51 [Cu2+]/[Zn2+] 1.40 ± 1.11 1.07 ± 0.27 0.42 ± 0.15 [Ca2+] (mg L-1) 85.15 ± 23.36 97.57 ± 27.92 127.47 ± 27.99 [Mg2+] (mg L-1) 68.29 ± 35.26 72.64 ± 27.41 114.12 ± 52.12 3.2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Selection of the optimal tumor marker group Some valuable markers act as the central indices that can meet the requirement for cancer diagnosis.</sentence>
    <sentence>These central indices may be chosen from the above tumor markers by removing other minor indices.</sentence>
    <sentence>For this purpose, multiple logistic regression analysis was applied to select the central indexes into an optimal tumor marker group.</sentence>
    <sentence>The results were obtained by the stepwise regression procedure and shown in Table 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Summary of the stepwise procedure.</sentence>
    <sentence>Step Entered Variable Number Score Wald Pr &gt; Removed In Chi-Square Chi-Square Chi-Square 1 CEA 1 83.5134 0.0001 2 [Cu2+]/[Zn2+] 2 34.2632 0.0001 3 Sialic acid 3 28.0763 0.0001 4 [Ca2+] 4 15.0212 0.0001 5 Gastrin 5 15.9904 0.0001 6 NSE 6 9.9925 0.0016 7 CA125 7 12.0897 0.0005 8 CA125 6 4.1467 0.0417 Analysis of the maximum probability estimation was carried out on the basis of MLR.</sentence>
    <sentence>The corresponding results are presented in Table 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>From the whole factors logistic regression model, all factors that were investigated are clinically significant, when the regression coefficient is minus, with the exception of calcium.</sentence>
    <sentence>Among these markers, CEA, [Cu2+]/[Zn2+], sialic acid, calcium, gastrin and NSE are particularly important to diagnose lung cancer.</sentence>
    <sentence>They were therefore selected to comprise an optimal tumor marker group.</sentence>
    <sentence>Table 4.</sentence>
    <sentence>Analysis of the maximum likelihood estimates.</sentence>
    <sentence>Variable Freedom degree Parameter estimate Standard error Wald chi-square Pr &gt; chi-square Standardized estimate Odds ratio INTERCP1 1 19.9935 5.7126 12.2494 0.0005 INTERCP2 1 37.5458 9.6173 15.2410 0.0001 CEA 1 −0.2839 0.0880 10.4103 0.0013 −1.889755 0.753 Gastrin 1 −0.0470 0.0163 8.2658 0.0040 −1.795253 0.954 NSE 1 −0.2148 0.0783 7.5337 0.0061 −2.464466 0.807 Sialic acid 1 −0.0187 0.0054 11.8367 0.0006 −1.815882 0.981 [Cu2+]/[Zn2+] 1 −5.2299 1.3857 14.2447 0.0002 −1.783718 0.005 [Ca2+] 1 0.0688 0.0219 9.8872 0.0017 1.212898 1.071 3.3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Application of an ANN-based intelligent diagnosis system for lung cancer 3.3.1.</sentence>
    <sentence>Selection of the training and test subset samples One hundred from 140 samples were randomly selected as a training subset of the neural network.</sentence>
    <sentence>These samples included 35 normal people, 30 patients with benign lung diseases and 35 patients with lung cancers.</sentence>
    <sentence>An additional 40 samples were collected from 15 normal people, 10 patients with benign lung diseases and 15 with lung cancer.</sentence>
    <sentence>These 40 samples were used as a test subset to examine the predictive performance of the neural network.</sentence>
    <sentence>Investigation of neural network adaptability We used the back-propagation (BP) network composed of units of three plenitudinous connection layers.</sentence>
    <sentence>The number of units in the input layer, m = 6, the hidden one, n = 3, and the output one, p = 1.</sentence>
    <sentence>We entered 100 samples into the network as a trial subset for training.</sentence>
    <sentence>Training speed was set at α = β = 0.7, with error threshold value δ = 0.05.</sentence>
    <sentence>The normal group was regarded as the first type and the expectation output value was 0.1; the benign group was regarded as the second type and the expectation output value was 0.5, the lung cancer group was the third type and the expectation output value was 0.9.</sentence>
    <sentence>All samples are in the trial group trained by times 10,000, the network converges and the overall output error was 7.0%.</sentence>
    <sentence>The output values of samples of training subset are shown in Fig 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>From these results, it was concluded that if the output value of a sample was greater than 0.8, the sample could be judged as a lung cancer, whereas the output values for the benign diseases vary between 0.4 and 0.6.</sentence>
    <sentence>In addition, a normal control sample has the output value of less than 0.3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Importantly, the results presented in Fig 2 indicate that the discrimination rate of the network to the sample is 95% (95/100) (see the sixth formula below).</sentence>
    <sentence>Discriminating results of three groups in the training subset Fig 2.</sentence>
    <sentence>Discriminating results of three groups in the training subset.</sentence>
    <sentence>The results were obtained from the BP-based ANN program.</sentence>
    <sentence>The output values of the malignant samples (Discriminating results of three groups in the training subset) are greater than 0.8.</sentence>
    <sentence>By contrast, most of the benign samples (Discriminating results of three groups in the training subset) ranged between 0.4 and 0.6, but two samples are smaller than 0.4 whereas additional two samples are greater than 0.6.</sentence>
    <sentence>The actual outputs of the normal samples (Discriminating results of three groups in the training subset) are almost smaller than 0.3, with an only exception that exceeds 0.3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Categorization of test subset in the neural network examination Besides the 100 samples of the training subset, we took the remaining 40 samples as the test subset which included 15 normal samples, 10 samples with benign diseases, and 15 samples with lung cancers.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ANN was tested and calculated as before.</sentence>
    <sentence>The categorized results are shown in Fig 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>A remarkable circumscription was found between the lung cancer and normal control groups.</sentence>
    <sentence>An additional circumscription was also observed between the lung cancer and benign lung disease groups.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, some of normal samples were prone to be misjudged as benign disease samples.</sentence>
    <sentence>From these results we draw a conclusion that the prediction rate of BP network reaches 85.0% (34/40) (see the seventh formula).</sentence>
    <sentence>Predictive results for three groups in the examining subset Fig 3.</sentence>
    <sentence>Predictive results for three groups in the examining subset.</sentence>
    <sentence>The results were obtained from the BP-based ANN program.</sentence>
    <sentence>The output values of the malignant samples (Predictive results for three groups in the examining subset) were greater than 0.8, whereas the values of the benign samples (Predictive results for three groups in the examining subset) were ranged between 0.4 and 0.6.</sentence>
    <sentence>In addition, five samples (NO.</sentence>
    <sentence>2, 3, 4, 7, 9 and 12) of the normal samples (Predictive results for three groups in the examining subset) were misjudged as the benign type in the test subset.</sentence>
    <sentence>Effects of different marker numbers on the output of their group-based ANN It is unclear whether different numbers of tumor makers influence the ANN-based diagnosis of lung cancer.</sentence>
    <sentence>We tried to choose four and three from the above six tumor markers according to the stepwise regression procedure.</sentence>
    <sentence>For example, a group consisted of four tumor makers CEA, [Cu2+]/[Zn2+], sialic acid, and [Ca2+], the former three of which comprised an additional group.</sentence>
    <sentence>The structure and parameters of the corresponding neural network were similar to those described above.</sentence>
    <sentence>The rates of discrimination and prediction were formulated and are shown in Table 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>These results indicate that either discrimination or prediction rates vary with the number of tumor markers.</sentence>
    <sentence>These two rates could gradually be improved by increasing the number of tumor markers.</sentence>
    <sentence>As anticipated, the group including twelve tumor markers is the best one among these groups tested.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is notable however that no significant difference is observed in the two groups comprising six or twelve tumor markers (Table 5).</sentence>
    <sentence>This suggests that an optimal group of six tumor markers may satisfy clinical demands.</sentence>
    <sentence>(6) (7) Table 5.</sentence>
    <sentence>Comparison of discrimination and prediction rates in different tumor marker groups.</sentence>
    <sentence>Number of tumor markers 3 4 6 12 Number in training set 100 100 100 100 Discrimination rate 72% 64% 95% 97% Number in test set 40 40 40 40 Prediction rate 62.5% 70% 87.5% 90% 3.3.5.</sentence>
    <sentence>Comparison of the neural network with the traditional statistical method The normal values of tumor markers may be derived by the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve (Kang, 1999), in which the point for the highest sensitivity but the lowest false positive rate can be found.</sentence>
    <sentence>The sensitivity, specificity and accuracy were calculated according to the following formula 8–10 (Li, 1998).</sentence>
    <sentence>The optimal group of six tumor markers was dealt with either ANN or the traditional metric medical statistical method (Table 6).</sentence>
    <sentence>Our results indicate that the ANN-based diagnosis is superior to the traditional method, because specificity has remarkably improved from 72.0% to 100.0% and accuracy increased from 71.4% to 92.8%.</sentence>
    <sentence>(8) (9) (10) Table 6.</sentence>
    <sentence>Comparison of the neural network with traditional statistical method.</sentence>
    <sentence>Evaluation index BP network Metric medical science The optional tumor markers group The optional tumor markers group Sensitivity (%) 100.0 98.0 Specificity (%) 100.0 72.0 Accuracy (%) 92.8 71.4</sentence>
  </section>
  <section name="Discussion">
    <sentence>The value of a single tumor marker is limited in diagnosing lung cancer, and therefore it is advisable to combine several markers that have complementary sensitivities (Zhao et al., 2005).</sentence>
    <sentence>In the quantitative determination, sensitivity is not consistent with the specificity; there exists a trade-off relationship between sensitivity and specificity because they often vary with the critical values (Wu, 2002).</sentence>
    <sentence>The optimal critical value can usually be chosen using the ROC curve (Ren et al., 2000).</sentence>
    <sentence>The vertical axis of ROC is expressed by true positive rate as the sensitivity, whereas its horizontal axis is shown by false positive rate (which is equal to 100% minus the value of specificity).</sentence>
    <sentence>Different critical values of the ROC can reflect the changes between sensitivity and specificity.</sentence>
    <sentence>Therefore, the critical value of tumor markers is often evaluated by the ROC.</sentence>
    <sentence>From this it is deduced that the normal critical values of CEA, [Cu2+/Zn2+], sialic acid, [Ca2+], gastrin and NSE are 20 μg L-1, 1.0, 1040 mg L-1, 100 mg L-1, 95 ng L-1, 18 μg L-1, respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>Combinative determination of all these six tumor markers indicated that the sensitivity, specificity and accuracy are 98.0% (49/50), 72.0% (36/50), and 71.4% (100/140), respectively.</sentence>
    <sentence>The sensitivity for 6 markers of lung cancer combined is higher than that obtained from a single marker.</sentence>
    <sentence>By contrast, specificity of the six-marker combinative determination is to varying degrees reduced, and its accuracy is relatively lower than that for a single tumor marker.</sentence>
    <sentence>This problem has been solved by an ANN technology.</sentence>
    <sentence>Although a lot of algorithms for the ANN have been developed, the back-propagation algorithm is widely used in various areas.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, the back-propagation algorithm has some disadvantages, such as easily local minimization and slow convergence rate.</sentence>
    <sentence>Thus, some scientists use an improved algorithm by including the item of the momentum; it can effectively accelerate convergence to prevent from oscillating (Zhang, Wu, &amp; Wu, 2007).</sentence>
    <sentence>We have selected a momentum coefficient to be 0.95.</sentence>
    <sentence>The ANN-based approach is superior to a traditional medical statistical method.</sentence>
    <sentence>It is because ANN can identify the trends and features of relatively complex information.</sentence>
    <sentence>This network can also act as a pattern processor by two phases in the information processing.</sentence>
    <sentence>We have developed an intelligence system for diagnosing lung cancers.</sentence>
    <sentence>Our results demonstrated that the diagnosis specificity was remarkably improved from 72.0% to 100.0%, and the accuracy was also increased from 71.4% to 92.8%.</sentence>
    <sentence>While the ANN-based system can also distinguish between benign lung diseases and normal people with a total accuracy rate of 91.1%.</sentence>
    <sentence>However, lack of discrimination between benign lung diseases and normal group suggest that the optimal tumor marker group-based ANN diagnosis system is neither specific nor sensitive enough to distinguish these two groups.</sentence>
    <sentence>This is because the optimal tumor marker group was selected to primarily distinguish lung cancer from either benign lung diseases or normal control.</sentence>
    <sentence>In summary, we have proved that the measurement combination of a tumor marker group is more powerful than a single marker.</sentence>
    <sentence>Mathematical evaluation of a tumor marker profile employing ANN modeling has demonstrated that the optimal tumor maker group can improve the efficiency of tumor markers applied in the diagnosis of lung cancer.</sentence>
    <sentence>The set-up of this ANN-based system is useful to extensively survey the high-risk group and also to screen patients with either lung cancer or benign disease.</sentence>
    <sentence>Thus, this system will play a positive role in cancer detection and prevention.</sentence>
  </section>
</article>
